<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno primo et secu[n]do Philippi &amp; Mariæ actes made at a Parliament begon and holden at Westminster, the xij day of Noue[m]ber, in the fyrst and second year of the reigne of Our Soueraigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, Kinge and Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Jerusalem, and Irelande, defendours of the faith, princes of Spayne &amp; Sicile, archdukes of Austria, dukes of Millaine, Burgondie and Brabant, counties of Haspurge, Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the dissolution of the same, beinge the xvj daye of January then next ensuing, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9448.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22798776</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22798776</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 500:11 or 1776:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno primo et secu[n]do Philippi &amp; Mariæ actes made at a Parliament begon and holden at Westminster, the xij day of Noue[m]ber, in the fyrst and second year of the reigne of Our Soueraigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, Kinge and Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Jerusalem, and Irelande, defendours of the faith, princes of Spayne &amp; Sicile, archdukes of Austria, dukes of Millaine, Burgondie and Brabant, counties of Haspurge, Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the dissolution of the same, beinge the xvj daye of January then next ensuing, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Mary I, Queen of England, 1516-1558.</author>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xxxiiii leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Iohannis Cavvodi ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.L.V [1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B⁴ C-F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Title in illustrated border.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 500:11 identified as STC 9448.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Harvard University Library and Merton College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno primo etſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do Philippi &amp; Mariae. Actes</hi> made at a Parliament begon and holden at Weſtminſter, the .xii day of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in the fyrſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond year of the reigne of our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, kinge and Quene of England, Fraunce Naples Ieruſalem, and Irelande, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours of the faith, princes of Spayne &amp; Sicile, Archdukes of Auſtria, Dukes of Millaine, Burgondie and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, counties of Haſpurge Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the diſſolution of the ſame, beinge the .xvi. days of Ianuary then next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were enacted as foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:2"/>
            <head>The Table,</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N act touchinge letters patentes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and other wrytynges to be ſigned by the Quenes Maieſtie. Ca. i.</item>
               <item>An act for the reformation of exceſſe in apparel. Ca. ii</item>
               <item>An acte againſt ſeditious wordes and rumours. Cap. iii.</item>
               <item>An act for the puniſhment of certayne perſons callynge them ſelues Egiptians. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte to reſtrayne carying of corne, victuals, and woode, ouer the Sea. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>An acte for the reniuing of three ſtatutes, made for the punyſhment of hereſyes. Cap. vi.</item>
               <item>An act that perſonnes dwellyng in the countrey ſhal not ſell dyuers wares in cyties and townes corporate by retayle. Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>An act repealing al ſtatutes, articles, and prouiſions, made agaynſte the ſea apoſtolyke of Rome, ſynce the twenty yeare of kynge Henrye theyght, and alſo for the eſtabliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of al ſpyrytual, &amp; eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, and hereditamentes conueyed to the laytye. Cap. viii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punyſhment of trayterous wordes agaynſt the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maieſtie. Cap. ix</item>
               <item>An acte wherby certaine offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kinges and Quenes Maieſties iſſue. Cap. x</item>
               <item>An acte for the puniſhmente of bunginge in of counterfeyte coyne of forrayne realmes, being curraunte within this realme, Ca. xi</item>
               <item>An acte touchinge the impoundinge of diſtreſſes. Ca. xii.</item>
               <item>An act appoyntynge in order to Iuſtices of peace, touching the vail ment of pryſoners. Cap. xiii.</item>
               <item>An act for the making of ruſſels ſatens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples in Norwyche. Cap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte to confyrme the liberties of the lorde Marchers in Wales. Cap. xv.</item>
               <item>An act for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap. xvi</item>
               <item>An act touchyng leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpyrytuall perſons. Cap. xvii</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:2"/>
            <head>An acte touchynge letters patentes and other wrytynges to beſigned by the Quenes Maieſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">The fyrst Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the Parliamente begonne and holden at Weſtminſter, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day of Apryll, in the fyrſte yeare of the reigne of oure mooſte dreade and gratious Souetaygne Ladye the Queenes Maieſtye, &amp; there con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinued and kept til the diſſolution of the ſame being the fift day of Maye, then next folowinge, one acte was made touching tharticles of her high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes moſt noble mariage. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which acte amongeſte other thinges it was enacted, ordred, &amp; eſtabliſhed by the auctority of the ſaid parliament that all and ſinguler giftes, grauntes, letters patentes, exchanges, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firmations, leaſes, &amp; other writinges, whiche after the ſaid mariage and during the ſame ſhoulde paſſe and be made, of any benefices, offices, landes, reuenues and fruites, or of any of them, ſhoulde be intite led and made in the names of our Soueraigne Lord the king, and of her moſt excellent highnes, whether his Maieſtye ſhoulde be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent within the realmes and dominions of her hyghnes, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in any of them, or abſent. And that the ſame giftes, grauntes, letters paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, eſchaunges, confirmations, leaſes, and other writinges, ſo ſette forth and made, ſhoulde be ſealed, and firmed with the ſigne manuel of her highnes, and the ſame ſo ſigned &amp; ſealed with the greate ſeale of this realme or with ſuch ſeal as hath ben accuſtomed, ſhould be by thauctoritie of the ſaid parliament, demed, adiudged, declared, and pronounced, to be as good perfect, and of like force, ſtrength, &amp; effecte in the lawe, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, agaynſt our ſayd Soueraigne Lorde and Lady, the king and the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtyes, and her hyghnes heires and ſucceſſours, as yf her mayeſtye had ben at the tyme of the making thereof, ſole and vnmaried, and that all gyftes grauntes, letters patentes, eſchaunces, confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s leaſes and other wrytynges, whiche after the ſayde mariage, and durynge the time of the ſame, ſhould paſſe and be made of the ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefices, offyces landes, reuenues, and fruites, or of anye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto the ſigne manuall of her hyghnes, ſhould not be ſette made, or put ſhalbe by thaucthorytye of the ſayde parlyament, from to tyme demed, adiudged, aceepted, taken, and decreed, to be of no force, ne ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect but vtterly fruſtrate and voyde in the lawe, to all intentes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb facs="tcp:25750:3"/>and purpoſes the ſayde marjage pranye law, vſage or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtanding, as by the ſayde act more at large doth appeare.</p>
            <p>Sithence the making of which Statut, and the ſolmntſation of the ſayde mariage the queenes moſt excellent maieſtye hath bene greatly moleſted greued, and troubled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> often ſigning of letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, giftes, grauntes, eſchaunges, leaſes, and other wrytynges, concerning and touchinge benefices, offices, andes, reuenues, and fruites, made and graunted by and from but ſayd ſoueraygne lorde the kynge and her highnes, to ſundrye of theyr moſt louynge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to whome alſo it hath bene, and is, no ſmal charge to attend, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſſuche tyme as they may procure and obteyne the ſigne manuell of her highnes, vnto their ſayde letters patentes, gyftes, grauntes, ef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunges, confirmations; and leaſes, without whith ſigne the fame are vtterly voyde by force of the ſayde ſtatute, to the great daunger, loſſe, and vtter vndoing of diuers perſons, that haue lately boughte purchaſed or obtayned of our ſayd ſoueraigne Lorde and Lady, the kyng and Quenes maieſties, diuers landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes to theyr great coſtes and charges.</p>
            <p>For remedy wherof be it enacted by the auctoritie of this preſent parliamente, that the ſayde braunthe or article touchinge or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng only the ſigning of letters patentes, giftes grauntes, eſchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, confirmations leaſes or of other writinges, for any landes, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, offices, reuenues, friutes, or other hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſhal be from henceforth clearely repelled and made fruſtrate and voyde, to alin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliamet, that al and ſinguler letters patentes touching or concernyuge anye gifte, graunte eſchaungs, confirmation leaſe or other writinge the whiche ſithence the ſayde mariage hath paſſed, and be made of anye benefices offices manoures landes tenementes reuenues fruytes, lybertyes or other hereditamentes or of any of them, in the names of our mooſte dread Soueraygne Lorde and ladye, the kynge and the Quenes maieſties (the waraunte or writinge, or warauntes or wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges wherof being ſigned with her hyghnes ſigne manuel, in ſuch fourme order and degree, as the ſame heretofore haue bene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſigned, when her highnes was ſole and vnmaryed) ſhalbe by auctoritie of this preſent parliament, of the ſame like force, ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth and effecte in the lawe, to al intentes conſtructions and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as yf the ſame were or had bene ſigned by her highnes ligne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel and as yf her maieſtie had bene at the tyme of the makyng ther of ſole and vnmaryed, and as they were before the makynge of the ſayde acte. The ſayde eſtatute, or any braunche, or article therein con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:3"/>
            <head>☞ An act for the reformation of exceſſe in apparell.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The ſeconde Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that no perſon borne within this realme, or the domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nions of the ſame, other then the ſon and heyre appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt of a knight, or other then ſuch as maye diſpend xx.li. by the yere in landes, offices, fees, or other yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye reuenues for terme of lyfe, or be worth in goodes two. C.li. ſhall after the fyrſte daye of Apryll nexte comming, weare any manet of fylke in, or vpon his hatte, bonet, nyghtcappe, gyrdle, ſeabberde, hoſe, ſhoes, or ſpnrre leathers, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne of thre monethes impryſonment, and forfeytures of .x.li. for euery dayes wearing con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the tenour of this act.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthorytie aforeſayde, that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Aſſiſes, in theyr circuities, Iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions ſheriffes in their turnes, Stewardes in letes and lawe dayes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iors, ſhieriffes, and Baylyffes of cities Boroughes, &amp; townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate in theyr courtes, ſhall and maye enquyre, here and determyne from tyme to time, al and euery the ſaid offences, committed, or done within the limittes of theyr ſeueral iuriſdictions and aucthorities, and where any ſuche forfeytures ſhal happen to be found within the precincte of any citie, bourough, towne corporate, lete or lawe daye, then the Maior, ſherif, &amp; Bayliffes of the ſaide cities, boroughes, and townes, and owner of the ſayde lete or lawe dayes, to haue the one moytye of the ſayde forfeytures, and thother moytie to be to any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte of this realme that wyll ſue for the ſame in any court of recorde by action information, byll, or otherwyſe, in which no wager of law protection, or aſſoigne ſhalbe allowed. And where ſuche forfeyture ſhalbe founde out of any citie, boroughe, towne, lete, or lawe day, that the moytie of al ſuch forfeitures, ſhalbe to the kyng and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, and the heyres of the Quene, and thother moytie therof to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theyr ſubiectes, that wyl ſue for the ſame by byll, playnt, action, information, or otherwiſe in any court of record as is aforeſayde, in which no wager of lawe, protection, or eſſoygne ſhalbe admytted or allowed. And that al and euery ſuch perſon and perſons, as haue auc toritye by vertue of this acte, to heare and determine the premyſſes may vpon the conuiction of euery ſuche offender award proces vnto the ſhyryf of any ſhyre within this realme, for the apprehenſion of the ſayd offender, which beinge apprehended, ſhall be committed by the ſhyrefe vnto the gaole of the ſayde ſhyre there to remayne withoute bayle or maynpryſe vntyl the ſayde offendoure hath payde the forfey ture wherein he is ſo conuicted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthorytye aforeſayde, that yf any perſon or perſones of what eſtate condition or degree ſoeuer he or they be, after the ſaid firſt day of April next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, knowing any ſeruaunte or ſeruauntes of his or theyrs to offende contrarye to this act, doo not put the ſame oute of his or theyr ſeruice, but ſhall kepe in his or theyr ſeruice the ſame offendoure or offendours by the ſpace of xiiii. dayes next after ſuch knowledge had; or els beynge ſo put oute of his or their ſeruice ſhall retaine the ſame offendour or offendours to his or theyr ſeruice agayne within one yere next enſuing the time of committing of any ſuche offence, the ſame perſon or perſons, ſo ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or retayninge agayne in or to his or theyr ſeruice, any ſuche ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt or ſeruauntes offending contrary to the tenoure of this acte, as is aforeſayd, ſhall for euery his or theyr offence forfeyt, c.li. of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full moneye of England, the moytye whereof to be to the kynge and Quenes maieſties vſe, and the heyres and ſucceſſours of the quene, and the other moytie to hym that wyllſue for the ſame in any courte of record, by action, byl plaint information or otherwyſe, wherein no wager of law eſſoygne or protection ſhalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaye and be it enacted that this acte, or anye thyng therin conteyned, ſhall not extend to any perſon veynge of, or aboue the degree of a knyghtes ſonne or doughter, or veynge wyfe to anye of them, nor to ſuch as haue bene, be, or ſhalbe Maioure, Baylife, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman or head officer in any city, boroghe, or towne corporate, or to the wyfe of any of them, nor to any of the kynges or Queenes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes in ordinary wages attendaunt, and wearynge the kynges or Quenes ordinary liueries, but that they and euery of them, maye vſe and weare as they or any of them might lawfully vſe and weare before the makyng of this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo that no perſonne ſhalbe compelled by this acte, to put away his prentiſe or hyreb ſeruaunte before thende of the terme before agreed betwene them, nor that any mayſter ſhal forfeyt or loſe any pame or forfeyture for the keping of his prentiſe or hyred ſeruant after his offence, contrary to this act, vnto thend of the terme before agreed betwene them. Any thyng aboue ſayde to the contrary nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandynge.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo, that women may weare in theyr eappes, hattes, gyrdles, and hoodes, as they or anye of them myghte vſe and weare lawfully before the makynge of this acte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An acte agaynſt ſeditious wordes and rumors.</head>
            <head type="sub">The thyrde Chapter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Horeis is conteyned as well in the Statute of Weſtm. the fyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, as in the Statute made at Gloceſter the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde yere of the raygne of kynge Rychard the ſecond, that no man ſhoulde be ſo hardye to contryue, ſpeake, or tell anye falſe newes, lyes, or other ſuthe lyke falſe thynges of Prelates, Dukes, Earles, Baronnes, and other Nobles and Peares of the realme, or of the Chauncelloure, Treaſurer, cierk of the prmye ſeale, Stewarde of the kinges houſhold, Iuſtices of the one hauche or of thother, or of any of the great officers of this realm. And that euery ſuch offender ſhoulde ve taken and impriſoned, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſuchtime as he had brought him or them forth which did ſpeake the ſame. And where alſo at a parſiamente holoen at Cambridge in the .xli. ye are of the reygne of the ſayd kynge Rycharde, it was alſo enacted, that where anye ſuche offender as is aforeſayde ſhoulde be taken and imprifoned, and could not finde him of whome he hearde thoſe newes whiche he ſpake, as is aforeſaid, that then the ſame ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker ſhould be puntſhed by the adniſe of the counſayle, as by the ſame actes amongeſt other more playnly do and may appeare.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſente parliamente, that all and euery the ſayde former actes and Statutes ſhalbe and remaine in their full force ſtrengthe and effecte to all intentes, conſtructions and purpoſes. And ſurther that Iuſtices of the peace in euery Shire Citie, and towne corporate, within the limittes of theyr ſeueral com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſions, ſhall by auctoritye of this preſent act, haue ful power to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, he are and determine the cauſes aboueſayde, in the ſayde two fyrſt actes ſpecified, and to put the ſayd two fyrſt ſtatutes and euery braunthe in theim conteyned in due execution that from henceforth condigne puniſhement be not deferred from ſuche offenders.</p>
            <p>And for as much as diuers and ſundrye malicions &amp; euyll dyſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons maliciouſly, ſeditiouſely, rebelliouſlye, and vnnaturaliye contrary to the duery of their ſidelities and allegiaunces haue now of late not onely ymagined, inuented practiſed, ſpoeken and ſpredde abrode diuers and ſundry lalſe, ſeditious and ſciaunderous newes. rumors, ſayinges, and tales agaynſt our mooſt dreade Soueraigne lorde and kyng, and againſte oure mooſte naturall Soueraygne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and Quene, and agaynſte eyther of them, of whome we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to thinke euyliand much more to ſpeake euyll, whiche offence foundeth and is aſwel to the great diſhonor reproche and ſclaunder of theyr moſt excellent mateſties, as alſo to the great ſclaſider of this theyr realme, and other theyr dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but alſo haue deuiſed, made written printed publiſhed and lette forth diuers heynous, ſeditious and ſclaunderous writinges rymes ballades, letters papers and bokes, intending and practiſing therby to moue and ſtyrre ſeditions diſcozde diſcention and rebellion within this realme, to the greate
<pb facs="tcp:25750:5"/>perill and daunger of the ſame. Forauoy dinge wherof, be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent Parliament, that if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, after the, xx. day of February next enſuing, and after open Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamation made of this Acte, ſhal maliciouſly, of his or theyr ymani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſpeake any falſe ſeditions, and ſlaunderous newes, rumors ſayings, or tales of our ſaid Soueraigne lord and king, or of out ſaid moſt naturall Soueraignelady and quene, that then all and euerye ſuch perſon and perſones ſo offendyng, being therof conuicted or at tainted, in forme hereaſter, in this act expreſſed, ſhal for euery fyrſt of fence, in ſome market place within the ſhyre, citie or Borough, wher or neare vnto the place where the ſaid wordes were, or ſhalbe ſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, be ſet openly vpon the pylory, by the Sheriffe or his miniſters, if it ſhall fortune to be without any citie or towne corporate. And yf it happen to be within ſuche citie or towne corporate, then by the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal officer or officers of ſuch citie or towne corporate, or his or their miniſters, and there to haue both his eares cutte of, onleſſe he paye one hundreth poundes to the Kyſnge and quenes highnes vſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one moneth next after iudgement geuen of his ſayd offence, and alſo ſhall ſuffer impriſonmente by the ſpace of three monethes after ſuch his or theyr execution.</p>
            <p>And it is likewiſe enacted by thauctoritye aforeſayd, that al and euery perſon and perſons, which after the ſayde daye, and after Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation made of this act, ſhal malicioufly ſpeake anye falſe ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſlaunderons newes, rumors, or tales to the flaunder and reproche of our ſayde Soueraygne lord the kyuge, or of oure ſayde moſt natural Soueraygne ladye the queene, of the ſpeakynge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portynge of any other, that then all and euerye ſuche perſone or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo ſpeaking and reportyng, being therof conuicte or attaynted, in forme hereafter in this act expreſſed, ſhall for euery ſuch offence in ſome market place within the ſhyre, citie, boroughe, or towne, where or nere vnto the place where the ſayd wordes were or ſhalbe ſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and reported, be ſet openly vpon the pyllorye by the ſhyrif or his miniſters, if it ſhall fortune to be withoute any citie or towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and if it ſhall happen to be within any citie or to wne corporate, then by the principal officer or officers of ſuch citie or town corporate or his or their miniſters, and there to haue one of his eares cut of, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he paye one. C. markes to the kinges and queenes hyghnes vſe, within one moneth next after iudgement geuen of his ſayde offence and alſo ſhall ſuffer impryſonmente by the ſpace of one moneth after his or their execution.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye perſon or perſons ſhall after the ſayde daye, and after Proclamation made as is aforeſayd, maliciouſly deuiſe, writ, print, or ſet forth anye manner of booke time, ballade, letter, or writinge, conteynynge anye
<pb facs="tcp:25750:5"/>falſe matter, clauſe or ſenfence of ſclaunder reproche and diſhonoure of the kyng and quenes maieſties, or of other of them, or to the enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taging, ſturring or mouing of any inſurrection or rebellion, within this realme, or any dominions belongynge to the ſame. Or whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall maliciouſlye procure anye ſuche booke, time, hallade letter, or writinge, written, prynted, or ſet forth (and the ſayde. offence not being puniſhable by the Statute made in the .xx.ii. yere of the reigne of king Edward the third, concerning treaſons, or declaratis of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) that then and in euery ſuch caſe the offender and offenders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in after his or their conuiction or attaynder, ſhall for his or their firſt offence, in ſome market place within the ſhyre, city, or borow, wher the ſayd offence is or ſhalbe committed or done by the ſhyreffe or his miniſters, yf it ſhall fortune to be without anye citie or towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and yf within ſuch citie or towne corporate, then by the pryncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officer or officers of ſuche citie or towne corporate or by his or theyr miniſters, haue his and theyr ryght hand ſtricken of.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde. that yf anys perſon or perſons, beyng once lawfully conuicted of any of thoffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces aforeſayd now prouided to be puniſhed by the execution of loſſes of care, eares or hand as is aforeſayd, do after wardes eſtſones offende in any of the offences aforeſayde, that then he or they ſo offendynge ſhal ſuffer impriſonment durynge his or theyr lyues, withoute bayle or maynpryſe, and forfeyt and loſe to the kyng and quenes maieſties al his and theyr goodes and cattels.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by thauctority aforeſayd, that all Iuſtices of over &amp; determiner, within the limittes of their commiſſion Iuſtices of aſſiſe in their ſeuerall circuites, Iuſtices of gaole delyuerye, &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyces of peace, as wel within the liberties as without, within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of their ſeueral co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions in their generall ſeſſions, or other ſeſſions, whiche they or two of them whereof one of them to be of the <hi>Quormm,</hi> maye and ſhall apppoynt at theyr pleaſure, where and when nede ſhal requier &amp; ſhall by vertue hereof, haue ful power and aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruie to inquier, here and determine al and euery thoffences afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as in caſes and trial of fellony. And that the party indieted and artained, ſhal haue aduauntage of al maner of chalenges to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (peremptorye chalenge only except) as in trial of ſelony.</p>
            <p>And alſo that euery Iuſtice of peace within the limittes of hys commſſion ſhall haue full power and auctorytie to commit any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon beinge vehemently ſuſpected of any of the ſayd offences to ward, there to remayne without bayle or mainpryſe, vntyll he ſhalbe deliue red according to this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided always and be it enacted by thauctorytye aforſayde that no manar of perſon or perſons ſhalbe moleſted, or impeehed for anye of the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, concerning ſpeaking or reporting as is aforſayde
<pb facs="tcp:25750:6"/>oneles he or they be thereof accufed and conuicted wythin thre mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes, next after his or their ſayd offence ſo committed or done.</p>
            <p>And in caſe any perſon ſhalbe impryſoned foranye of the ſayde offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, concernyng ſpeakynge or reportynge, and not thereof conuycte, wythin three monethes, nexte after the offence ſuppoſed to be by him done and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted that then the perſou ſoo impryſoned ſhable ſet at lyberty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gee deteyned inpryſon.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted by auctoritie aforſaid, that eue ryeſuche Maſour, Maiours, Baylyffes, and other heade offycer and officers of cytyes, borowes, and townes corporate which haue or hereafter ſhal haue iuryſdictyon and auctorycye, wythin the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall limittes of thyroffyce or offyces, to hold and kepe ſeſſyons as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or iuſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace ſhall, and maye by auctoritie hereof, aſwell arreſt &amp; commite to ward, all and euerye perſon and perſons beynge vehemently ſuſpected of any of the offences aforeſaide, as alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to the execution, he aryng &amp; determining of euery the ſayd offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and to ſee, and make due execution therof, according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, meaninge and effecte of this preſente acte. Any thingein the ſame act heretofore made to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that the ſayd Iuſtice of peace, aſwel wythin liberties as without, the which ſhall for any the offences aforeſayde, commit any perſon or perſons to warde, as is aforeſayde, ſhall wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in tenne dayes next after ſuch committinge, with one other Iuſtice wherof one of them to be of the Quorum, direct their precepte to the Sherife or Sherifes of the countie where thoffence ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to other ordinary officer, if it be within any citye, or towne cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porate, where the Sherife can not intromit, commaundinge him or them by the ſame impanei and retourne, as they ſhall aſſigne, xxiiii. good and lawful men of his or theyr bayliwike or bayliwikes to en quyre of the ſayd offences or offences the whiche any ſuch perſon or perſons ſhalbe ſo impryſoned for. And thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within one moneth after the date of the ſaide precept to procede &amp; determine, as aboue is expreſſed. Euerye one of the ſame Iuſtices, vppon payne of .x.li. to be payed to the kyng and Quenes hyghneſſes, as often as they ſhalbe founden in defaulte of any the ſame.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo, and be it enacted, that thys act ſhalbe proclaimed in al the ſhyres within this realme, before the .xii. daye of Februarye next commyng to thintent that al perſons maye haue notice thereof and auoyd the peryl and daunger that myght enſue by offendynge agaynſt the ſame. And this acte to be only in force, vntill the ende of the next parlyament, and no longer.</p>
            <p>Promded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that none of the peares of this realme ſhalbe arreſted or impriſoned for any of the ſaid offences, but only by order or commaundemente.
<pb facs="tcp:25750:6"/>geuen from the kinge and quenes priuie counſayle, or of the heyres of the Quene, and that the ſayd peares, and euery of them, that ſhall bereafter fortune to be indicted of any thoffences aforeſayde, ſhalbe tryed by theyr peares, as before hath ben accuſtomed in caſes of trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon or fellonye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An acte for the puniſhment of certayne perſons callynge them ſelues Egiptians.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .iiii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in a parliament holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxij yere of the reygne of our late Soueraigne lorde kynge Henry theyght (for the auoyding and banyſhyng oute of this realme of certaine outlandiſh people, callynge them ſelues Egiptians, vſing no craſt nor feate of marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes for to lyue by, but going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place in greate companyes vſing great, ſuttel, and crafty meanes to deſceaue the kynges Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, bearing them in hand, that they by palmiſtry could tell mens and womens fortune, and ſo many tymes by craft and ſubteltie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the people of theyr moneye, and committed diuers greate and heynous fellonyes and robberies, to the great hurt &amp; diſceyte of the people). It was amongeſte other thinges then enacted, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of the makinge of the fayde acte, no ſuche perſonnes ſhoulde be ſuffered to come within this the kinges realme, vppon payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyture to the kyng al theyr goodes and cattels, and then to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to auoyd the realme within .xv. dayes next after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, vpon payne of impriſonment, &amp; ſuch perſons callynge theim ſelues Egiptians, as then were within this Realme, ſhoulde depart within .xvi. dayes nexte after proclamation of the ſayde acte vpon payne of impriſonment and forfeyture of all theyr goodes and cattels w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers other clauſes &amp; articles conteined in the ſayde act, as by the ſaid act more at large it appeareth. For aſmuch as dyuers of the ſayd company and ſuch other lyke perſonnes not fearynge the penalty of the ſayde Statute, haue enterpriſed to come ouer agayne into this realme, vſyng theyr old occuſtomed deuyliſhe and noughty practiſes and deuiſes, with ſuch abhominable lyuynge as is not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye Chriſtian realme to be permitted, named, or knowen, and be not duly punyſhed for the ſame, to the peryllous and euylexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of oure ſoueraygne lorde and ladye the kynge and the Queenes Maieſties mooſte louynge ſubiectes &amp; to the vtter and extreame vndoynge of diuers and many of them as euidently doth appeare.</p>
            <p>For reformation wherof be it ordeined and enacted by the kynge and quene our ſoueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the Lordes ſpyrytuall and temporall, and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this preſent parltame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that yf any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after the
<pb facs="tcp:25750:7"/>laſte daye of Ianuary next comming, do willingly tranſport, bringe and conuey into this realme of England or Wales, any ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s callinge them ſelfes or commonly called Egiptians, that then he or they ſo tranſportyng, bringing or conueying in, anye ſuche perſons, contrary to the true meaninge of this acte, ſhall forfeite and looſe for euery tyme ſo offending .xl. poundes of lawful money of Englande.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthority aforeſayde, that yf anye of the ſaid perſons called Egiptians, whiche ſhalbe tranſported and conueyed into this realme of England or Wales, as is aforeſaide, do continue &amp; remaine within the ſame, by the ſpace of one monethe, that then he or they ſo offendynge, ſhall by vertue of this acte, bede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and indged a fellon and fellons, and ſhall therefore ſuffer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death, loſſe of landes &amp; goodes, as in caſes of felony, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the common lawe of this realme, and ſhall vppon the tryall of them, or any of them, therin, be tried in the countie, and by thinhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the countie or place, where they or he ſhalbe apprehended or taken, and not <hi>per medietatem linguae</hi> and ſhal loſe the benefit and priuiledge of ſanctuary and clergye.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf the Egiptians or other perſons commonly callinge theim ſelues Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and euery of them now beyng within this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or Wales, do not depart out of the ſame within .xx. daies nexte after proclamation of this preſent acte ſhall be made, that then he or they whiche ſhall not depart within the ſaid time, accordinge to the true meaning of this acte, ſhall forfeyte and loſe all his and theyr goodes and cattels, and that then it ſhalbe lawfull to al and euery the kynge and the Quenes ſubiectes to ſeaſe the ſame, thone moytie thereof to be to the vſe of our ſoueraygne lord and lady the king and the quene and thother moytie therof to be to the vſe of him or them that ſhal ſo ſeaſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by thauctority aforeſayde, that yf the Egip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tians and other perſons commonly called Egiptians, and euerye of them now beinge within this realme of England or Wales, do not depart out, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, within .xl. dayes nexte after proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhalbe made of this act, that then he or they, which ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and anoyd within the ſayde tyme of .xl. dayes accordinge to the true meaning of this act, ſhalbe indged and demed according to the lawes of this realme of England a fellon and fellons, and ſhal ſuffer therfore paines of death, loſſe of landes and goodes as in other caſes of fellony and ſhalbe tryed as is aforeſayd, and without hauyng any benefite or prinilege of ſanctuary and clergye.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye perſon after the fyrſt day of Ianuary next comming, ſhall ſue for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hteyning of any licence, letter, or paſporte, for anye of the ſayde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:25750:7"/>called Egiptians, to abide or continue, within this realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland or Wales, contrary to the tenour of this acte, that then euerye ſuch perſon ſo ſuing, ſhal forfeyt and loſe for the ſame forty poundes, of lawefull money of Englande, and that euerye ſuche lycenſe, letter and paſport, ſhalbe by vertue of this acte, voyde, to al intentes &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, thone moytie of all which ſummes of moneye to be forfeited, as is beforeſaid, ſhalbe to the kyng and Quene our Soueraygne Lorde and Lady, and the other moyte therof to be to him or them, that wyll ſue for the ſame, in any court of record, by action of dect, byll, playnte, or information, wherin any eſſoigne, wager of lawe, nor protectyon, ſhalbe admitted and allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted by thaucth oritie aforeſayd, that thys preſent act, nor any thinge therein conteyned, ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, nor be hurtfull to any of the ſaide perſones, commonlye called Egyptians which within the ſayd tyme of twenty dayes nexte after the ſayde proclamation to be made, as is beforeſayde, ſhall leaue that noughtye ydle, and vngodly lyfe, and companye, and be placed in the ſeruice of ſome honeſt and able inhabitaunte or mhabytauntes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this realme, or that ſhal honeſtlye exercyſe hym ſelfe in ſome lawe full worke or occupation, but that he or they ſo continuing in ſeruyce or other lawful worke or occupation, ſhal duringe ſuche time as he or they ſhall ſo continue, be diſcharged of all paynes, and forfeitures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that this acte ſhal not in any wiſe extende to anye chyld or children, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing not aboue the age of .xiii. yeares, nor to any of the ſaid perſonnes, being nowe in priſon ſo that he or they ſo being in priſon, doo departe out of this realme, within .xiiii. dayes next after his or their deliuery out of pryſon, nor ſhall extend to charge anye maner of perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as acceſſary to any offence or offences, conteined or ſpecified in this eſtatute.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ An acte to reſtraine carrying of corne, victuals, and wodde ouer the Sea.</head>
            <head type="sub">☞ The .v. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as ſundry good eſtatutes and lawes hath bene made within thys realme in the tiine of the Queenes highnes moſt noble progenitours that none ſhuld tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>port, carye or conueye oute of thys Realme into anye place in the parties beyond the ſeas any corne butter cheſe, or other victuall (except onelye for the vitalyng or the towne of Callys, Hames, &amp; Guyſnes, and the marches of the
<pb facs="tcp:25750:8"/>ſame, vpon dyuerſe great paynes and for faytures in the ſame contei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, that norwithſtandyng many and ſundre couetous and vnſacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſenes, ſekyng their onely ſucres, and gaynes, hath, and dayly doeth cary and conueigh innumerable quanticie aſwel of corne, cheſe butter, &amp; other victual, as of wod out of this realme, into the parties beyond the ſeas. By reaſon whereof the ſayd corne, vyctual &amp; woode are growen vnto a wonderfull dear the, and extreme pryces, to the great detriment of the Common wealth of this your highnes realm and your faythfull fubiectes of the ſame.</p>
            <p>For remeby wherof, it may pleaſe your highnes that it may be enacted, and be it enacted by youre highnes by thaſſent of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that no maner of perſon or perſonnes, after the .xx. daye of Ianuary next commyng ſhal carye &amp; tranſport out of this realme by any Shippe, Craier, or other beſſell, whatſoeuer, into any place in the parties beyond the ſeas, or into the realme of Scotland, any wheat, rye, barleye, or other corne or grain growing within this Realme, or any malt made within the ſame, or any bere, butter, cheſe, heringe, or wodde, except onely to and for the victualing and furniture of the to wnes of Callyes, Hames, &amp; Guyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to the towne of Barwicke &amp; the marches of the ſame, wyth out ſufficient and laweful aucthoritie ſo to do, vpon the paines and pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nalties hereafter euſuyng, that is to ſay, thowner and owners of the ſayd ſhyppes and other veſſels, to forfeyte the ſayd ſhippes, crayers and other veſſels, with al their apparels, to them and euery of them belongyng, wherein the ſayde corne, butter, cheſe, herryng, victuall, or wodde, ſhalve ſo tranſported and caried, and the owners &amp; owner of the ſayd corne, butter, cheſe, hearynge, and wodde to forfeyte the double value of the ſame ſo caried, and conueied, and the maiſter and mareners of euery of the ſayd ſhippes craiers, and veſſels for euerye ſuch offence, to forfeyte all their goodes, and to be impriſoned, by the ſpace of one whole yeare without bayle or maynepryſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further cuacted by thauctoritie aforeſaid, that yf anye perſon or perſones, after the ſayde twenty day of Ianuary do cary &amp; conueye awaye by Boote, Crayer, or other veſſell, or otherwpſe anye wheate, tye, bareley, malte, or other corne or crayne, or any beare, but<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter cheſe, herryng, or wodde to any Shippe or veſſett beinge on the Seas, or within any Hauen, creke, or other place of the bordre of this Realme to be tranſported, caried, and conueyed into any place in the parties beyonde the Seas, or into the realme of Scotland, without ſufficient aucthoritie ſo to doo, that then euery owner of the ſaid vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualls corne, and other thynges aboueſayd ſoo tronſported or caried and the owner and owners of enery ſuch bote or Veſſel and the bore menne and mareners of the ſame ſhall looſe forteyte, and ſuffer all
<pb facs="tcp:25750:8"/>ſuch forfaytures, paynes, and penalties as is aboue rehearſed, thone moytie of al, and euerye which forſayture or forfaitures, to be to the kynge and Quenes hyghnes, theyr heyres and ſucceſſours, and tho ther moytie to him or them, that wyl ſue for the ſame by byl, informa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, attion of debte, or otherwyſe in any of the kynge and Queenes hyghnes courtes of recorde, in which actyon, byll, or ſuite, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunte ſhal not wage his lawe nor haue any eſſoygne or protectyon to him allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaid, that yf any perſon or perſons ſhall obtayne of the kyng and Queenes maieſties, ther hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or ſucce ſſours, or of any of them, any licence to eary and tranſport any corne, victual, or wodde, into any parries beyond theſe as, that if he or thei, to whom any ſuch licence, ſhalbe geaunted, or any other, to whom ſuch perſon or perſoues, hauynge ſuch lycence, ſhal giue, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſell his or their ſaid licence vnto, ſhall cary, and conucy or cauſe to be caried and conueyed any more corne .victuall. or wood then ſhalbe conteined in his or their ſaid licence ſhall forfeyte the treble value of the ſayd corne, victual, or wood ſo carried and traſported, withoute ſufficient auctoritie, and ſhal ſuffer impriſonment for one whole yere in the common gaole, where he ſhalbe apprehended, ther to remaine without bayle or mainepryſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon or perſones, after the ſaid .xx. day of Ianuary, that ſhal obteine, or haue any ſuch licence for tranſportynge and carying anye corne victuall or wodde, into any parties beyond the ſeas, ſhal ſhippe lade, and fraught the ſame, or anye parte thereof, at ſondrye places within this realme, but at one place certaine, vpon paine of forferture of the ſayd corne, victual &amp; wodde, and al his goodes &amp; cattels thoue moytie thereof to the kyng and Quenes inaieſties, their heires and ſucceſſours, and thother moytie to him or them that wyll ſue for the ſame by action of debte .byl, playnt information or otherwiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no wager of lawe, eſſoygne or protection ſhalbe to hym or them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>And for the better execution of this act, be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aſoreſaid, that all and ſinguler Iuſtices of peace, as well within the liberties as without, within their ſeuerall aucthorities &amp; commyſſions at any tyme, with in three yeares next after ſuch offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed, ſhall haue full powre and aucthoritie to enquire as well by the othes of twelue laweful men, as alſo to heare &amp; examine the mayſter, maiſtres, and mareners of the ſayde ſhyppes, crayers, &amp; other veſſels, and al, and euery other perſon and perſones, of all, and ſynguler the offenders agaynſte this preſent acte, and to here and determine the ſame offences, as they may, and ought to here and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine any other treſpaſſes, or offences.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſnyde, that at all time and times hereafter, when the common price of corne within thys Realme is, that wheat ſhall not excede the pryce of vl.s. viii.d. the quarter, and rye .iiii.s. the quarter, and bareley .iii. ſhillings the quarter, it ſhalbe laweful to euery perſon and porſons to cary and tranſport ouer the ſea, to any place beyonde the ſeas at their pleaſure of the ſayde kyndes of corne, ſo that it be not to the kyng and quenes enemies.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thautthoritie aforeſayde, that thys acte, ne any thing therein contained, ſhall extende to anye perſon or perſones for the neceſſary victeling of any ſhippe, ſhyppes, or other veſſells, but that they. and cuery of them, maye victaile the ſayd ſhyppes &amp; veſſels, as they mighte haue done before the making of this preſente acte. Thys acte or anye thynge therein conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaide, that thys acte, or any thinge therein conteined, ſhal not be preiudiciall or hurtefull vnto the Lord great admirall of Englande, for the tyme beinge or to the kyng and Quenes Maieſties furiſdiction of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miraltie, but that the ſayd Lord Admiral, or his deputy, or deputyes, may, and ſhall exercyſe .vſe. and execute al kynde of iuryſdyctyon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longyng to the ſea accordyng to his or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions, as they might lawefully haue. done heretofore. Thys acte, or anye thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ An acte for the reuiuing of three Eſtatutes made for the puniſhment of hereſies.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .vi. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the eſchuing and auoydinge of errons &amp; herefyes, which of late haue riſen, growen, and much increaſed within this Realme, for that the Ordynaryes haue wanted aucthoritie to procede agaynſt thoſe, that wer infected therwith, Be it therefore ordeyned and enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parlyamente, that the Statute made in the fyfte yere of the reigne of kynge Rycharde the ſecond, concerning the arreſting and apprehenſion of erronyous and hereticall preachers, and one other Statute, made in the ſeconde yeare of the reigne of king Henry the fourth, concernyng repreſſynge of hereſies, and punyſhment of heretikes, and alſo one other Eſtatute made in the Second yeare of the raygne of kynge Henrye the fyfre, concernyng the ſuppreſſyon of hereſye and lollardye, and cuerye Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, Braunche, and ſentence conteygned in the ſame thres ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:25750:9"/>actes, and euery of them, ſhall from the twenty daye of Ianuary next comming, be reuiued, and be in ful force, ſtrength, and effect, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenses, conſtructions &amp; purpoſes, for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ The tenor of the acte, made in the fyſt yeare of kynge Rychard, is as foloweth. Chapiter .v.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem foraſmuch as it is openly knowen, that there be diuers euill perſones within the realme going from cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie to countie, &amp; from towne to towne, in certaine habites, vnder dyſſimulation of great holines, &amp; with out the licence of the ordinaries of the places, or other ſufficient aucthoritie: preaching daylye, not onelye in churches &amp; churchyardes, but alſo in markets, faires, &amp; other ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where a great congregacion of people is, diuers ſermones contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hereſies, &amp; notorious errours, to the great embleamiſhing of the chriſten faith, and deſtruction of the Lawes, and of the eſtate of holye Churche, to the great pericle of the ſoules of the people, and of all the realme of England, as more plainelye is found, and ſufficientlye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, before the reuerent father in God the Archbiſhop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and the Biſhoppes, and other prelates, mayſters of diuinitie, and doctours, of Canon and of ciuile, and a greate parte of the clergye of the ſaid realme, ſpecially aſſembled for this cauſe, which perſones do alſo preach diuers matters of ſlaunder, to engender diſcord &amp; diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on betwixt diuers eſtates, of the ſaid realme, aſwel ſpirituall as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall in exciting of the people to the great peril of al the realm, which preachers cited or ſommoned before the ordinaries of the places, there to aunſwere of that where of they be impeched, wil not obeye to there ſummons and commaundementes, nor care not for their monycyons nor ſenſures of the holy Church, but expreſſely diſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, by their ſubtil and ingenious wordes, do drawe the people to here their Sermons, and do maintaine them in their errours by ſtronge hand, and by great routes. It is ordeyned and aſſented in this preſent Parliament that the kinges commiſſions be made and directed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sheryffes and other miniſters of our ſoueraigne Lord the kinge or other ſufficient perſons learned, and accordinge to the certificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the prelates therof to be made in the Chauncery, from time to time to arreſt all ſuche preachers, and alſo their fautours, mainteners and abbettours, and to holde them in arreſt and ſtrong priſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ii they wil inſtify them, accordyng to the lawe and reaſon of holy Church. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge wyll and commaundeth, that the Chauncellor make ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions at all times, that he by the prelates, or any of them ſhal be cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyfyed, and thereof required, as is aforeſayd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:10"/>
            <head>¶ The tenor of the ſecond acte, made in the ſecond yeare of kynge Henry the .iii. is as foloweth. Cha .xv.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem where as it is ſhewed to our Soueraygne Lord the king, on the behalfe of the prelates and Clergye of his realme of England in this preſente Parlyamente, that although the catholyke faith builded vpon Chriſt and by his Apoſtles, and the holye church ſufficientlye determined, declared, and approued, hath bene hether to by good and holy, and moſte noble progenitours of our ſoueraigne Lord the kyng in the ſaide Realme, emongeſte all the realmes of the worlde, moſt deuoutlye obſetued, and the Churche of Englande, by his ſaid moſt noble progenitours and aunceſtours, to the honoure of God, and the whole Realme aforeſaid, laudably endowed, and in her rightes and liberties ſuſteined, without that that the ſame faith, or the ſayd Church was hurte or greuouſlye oppreſſed, or ells perturbed by any peruerſe doctryne, or wicked heretical or crronious opinions, yet neuer the leſſe dyuers falſe and peruerſe people, of a certaine new ſecte of the ſayth, of the Sacramentes of the Churche, and the aucthorytie of the ſame, damnably thinking and agaynſt the lawe of god, and of the churche, vſurpyng the offyce of preachyng do pecuerſly and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlye, in dyurrſe places within the ſayd realme, vnder the colour of diſſimuled holines, preach and teach theſe dayes openly and priuely, diuers newe doctrines, and wycked heretical and erronious opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contrarye to the ſame fayth; and bleſſed determinations of the holye Churche. And of ſuche ſecte and wicked doctrine and opinions, they make vnlawefull couenticles, and coufederacies, they holde and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe ſcholes, they make and wryte bokes, they do wickedly inſtructe &amp; infourme people, and aſmuch as they maye excite and ſtirre them to ſedition and inſurrection and maketh gret ſtrife and diuiſion emong the people, and other enormities horrible to be heard, dayly doo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate and commit, in ſubuercion of the ſaid catholyke faith, and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of the holy churche, in diminucion of Gods honoure, and alſo in deſtruction of the eſtate, ryghtes, and liberties of the ſaide churche of England, by which ſecte and wicked and falfe preachynges, doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and opinions of the ſayd falſe and peruerſe people, not onely moſt greateſt peryl of the ſoules, but alſo manye more other hurtes, ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and peryls (which God prohibite) mighte come to thys Realme onleſſe it be the more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully and ſpedely holpen by the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in this behalfe, namely wher as the dioceſans of the ſaid realme cannot by their iuriſdiction ſpiritual without aide of the ſayde royall Maieſtie, ſufficiently, correcte the ſaide falſe and peruerſe people, nor refrayne their malice, becauſe the ſaid falſe and peruerſe people do go from Dyoces to Dyoces, and wil not appeare before the ſayd Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans, but the ſame Diocelans, and their iuriſdiction ſpiritual, and the
<pb facs="tcp:25750:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>kayes of the churche, with the cenſures of the ſame, doo vtterlye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne and diſpiſe, and ſoo there wicked preachinges and doctrines, doeth from daye to daye continue and eretciſe, to the hatrede of fyght and reaſon, and vtter deſtruction ordre and good rule. Vpon whych no welties and exceſſes aboue rehearſed. The Prelates and Cleargye aforeſayd, and alſo the commons of the ſayd realme, being in the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, praying our ſoueraigne Lord the kyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his roial highnes would voucheſafe in the ſayd parliamente, to pronide a conuenyente remedy, the ſame our ſoueraygne Lorde the kyng, gratioufly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the premyffes, and alſo the lawdable ſteppes of his ſaid moſt no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble progentiours and aunceſtours, for the conſeruation of the ſaid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fayth, and ſuſtentation of Goddes honour, and alſo the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the eſtate, ryghtes, and lyberties of the ſayde Churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, to the laude of God, and merite of our ſaide ſoueraygne Lorde the kynge, and proſperitie &amp; honour of al his ſayd realme, and for the eſchewynge of ſuch diſſentions, diuiſions, hurtes, ſlaunders, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryles, in time to come, and that thys wycked ſecte, preachynges, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes and opinions, ſhould from henceforth ceaſe, and be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayed, by thaſſent of the ſtates, &amp; other diſcrete men of the Realme, beyng in the ſayde parlyament, hathgraunted, ſtablyſhed, &amp; ordeined from henceforth, fermely to be ovſerned, that none within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid realm or any other dominions, ſubiectes to his royal maieſtie, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che openly or priuely without the licence of the Dyoceſan of the ſame place, fyrſt required and obteined, curates in their owne churches, &amp; perſones hetherto priuileged, and other of the canon law, graunted onelye excepte. Nor that none from hence for the anye thynge preache, holde teach, or inſtruct, openly or priuely, or make or writts anye boke contrary to the catholyke fayth or determination of the holye churche nor of ſuch, fecte and wicked doctrines and opinions, ſhall make anye conuenticles, or in any wiſe holde or evercyſe Scholes. And alſo that none from henceforth in any wiſe fauoure ſuche preacher, or maker of any ſuch, and lyke conuenticles or holdynge or exercyſyng Scholes, or makynge or wrytynge ſuche bokes, or ſo teachynge informynge, or exciting the people nor any of them maintaine, or in anywiſe ſuſtaine. And that al, and ſinguler hauyng ſuche bookes or anye wrytynges of ſuch wycked doctrine and opinions, ſhal really with effect delyuer, or cauſe to be deliuered al ſuch bokes and writtnges to the Dyoceſan of the ſame place, within .xi. dayes from the tyme of the proelamation of this or viuaunce and ſtatute. And yf any perſon or perſons, of what ſo euerkynd, eſtate, or condition that he or they be from henceforth do or attempt againſt the roial ordinaunce &amp; ſtatute aforeſaid in the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes or in any of them or ſuch bokes in the fourme aforeſaid do not dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then the dioceſan of the ſame place in his dioces ſuch perſonne or perſones in this behalfe defamed, or euidently ſuſpected &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:25750:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>may by the aucthoritie of the ſayd ordinarye and Statute, cauſe to be arreſted, and vnder ſaufe cuſtody in his priſones to be deteined, tyl he or they of the articles layed to him or them in this behalfe, doo canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally purge him or them ſelfe, or ells ſuche wicked ſecte preachynges, doctrynes, and heretical and erronious opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, do abiure, according as the lawes of the church, doth require, ſo that the ſayd dyoceſan by him ſelf, or his commiſſaries, do openly and iudicially procede againſt ſuch periones ſo arreſted, and remayning vnder his ſaufe cuſtodye to all effect of the lawe, and determine that ſame buſynes, according to the Canonicall decrees, within three monethes after the ſayde arreſt any lawfull impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ceaſſing. And yf any perſon in any caſe aboue expreſſed, be before the dioceſan of that place, or hys commyſſaryes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically conuict, then the ſame dioceſan may do to be kept in his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the ſayd perſon ſo conuict, for the maner of his defaulte, and after the qualitie of the offence, accordyng and as long as to hys diſcretion ſhall ſeme expedient, and moreouer to put the ſame perſon to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar court, except in caſes where he accordyng to the canonicall decree ought to be left, to paye to our ſoueraigne lord the kinge, his pecunier fine, accordyng as the ſame fyne ſhall ſeme competent to the dioceſan, for the maner and qualitie of the offence, in which caſe the ſame dyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan, ſhalbe bounde to certifye the kyng of the ſame fine in his eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, by his Lettre Patentes, ſealed with hys ſeale, to the effecte that ſuche fyne by the kynges aucthoritie, maye be requyred and leuied to his vſe of the goodes of the ſame perſon ſo conuycte. And if any perſon within the ſayd realme and dominions vpon the ſayde wycked prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges, doctrynes, opinions, ſchooles, and heretycall and erronious informations, or any of them be before the dioceſan of the ſame place, or his commiſſaries ſentencially conuyct &amp; the ſame wicked ſect, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges, doctrines, and opinions, ſcholes, and informations, do refuſe duely to abiure, or by the dyoceſan of the ſame place or his commyſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, after the abiuration made by the lame perſon pronounced, fal in to relapſe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accordinge to the holye canons, he oughte to be lefte to theſe culer courte, whervpon credence ſhalbe geuen to the dyoceſan of the ſame place, or to his commiſſaryes, in this behalfe, then the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffe of the countie of the ſame place, and Maior and ſheryffes or ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffe, or Mayor and Baylyffes of the Citie, Towne, and borow of the ſame countye next to the ſame dioceſan, or the ſayde Commiſſaryes, ſhalbe perſonailye preſent in preferryng of ſuch ſentences, when they by the ſame dioceſan, or his commiſſaries ſhalbe required, and they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſonnes and euerye of them after ſuche ſentence promulgate, ſhall receaue, and them before the people in an hygh place dooe to be brent: that ſuch punyſhmente maye ſtrike in feare to the myndes of other, wherby no ſuch wycked doctrine and heretical, and erronious opinions, nor their abbettours and fautours in the ſaid realme &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
<pb facs="tcp:25750:11"/>agaynſt the catholike faith, chriſten law &amp; determination of the holy church (which god prohibite) be fuſteined, or in any wyſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, in whiche al and ſinguler the premiſſes, concerninge the ſayde ordinaunce and ſtatute, the ſheriffes, maiors, and bailiffes of the ſaid counties, cities, boroughes, and townes, ſhalbe tendynge, aydynge. and ſupportyng to the ſayd dioceſans and their commiſſaries.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ The tenor of the thyrd act, made in the ſecond yere of kygne Henry the fift, is as foloweth. Cap. vii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem foraſmuch as great rumors, congregations, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections here in the realme of England by diuers of the kinges liege people, aſwel by them which wer of the ſect of hereſies commonly called lolardry, as by other of their confederatie, excitation, &amp; abbetment, nowe of late were made to thintent to adnul, deſtroy, and ſubuerte the chriſten faith, and the law of god and holy church within this ſame realm of England, and alſo to deſtroy the ſame our ſoueraine lord the king, and all other ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of eſtates of the ſame realme of England, aſwel ſpiritual as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and alſo al maner of policie and finally the lawes of the lande. The ſame our ſoueraigne lord the king, to the honour of god, and in conſeruation and fortification of the chriſten faith, and alſo in ſak ati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of his royal eſtate, and of theſtate of al his realme, willing againſt the malice of ſuch heretikes and lolardes to prouide a more open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy and puniſhment then hath ben had and vſed in the caſe hereto fore, ſo that for fear of the ſame lawes and puniſhment, ſuch hereſies and lolardries may the rather ceaſe in time to come, by the aduiſe and aſſent aforeſaid, at the prayer of the ſaide commons, hath ordeined &amp; eſtabliſhed, that firſt the chaunceloure, treaſurer, Iuſtices of the one benche and of thother. Iuſtices of peace, ſhirifes, mayors, and baylifs of cities and townes, and al other officers, hauinge gouernaunce of people, which now be, or hereafter for the tyme ſhalbe, ſhal make an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>othe in takyng of their charges and occupations, to put their hole po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer and diligence, to put out, and do to be put out, ceaſe and deſtroy al maner of hereſies and errors, commonly called lolardryes, within the places where they exerciſe their offices and occupations fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to tyme, with al theyr power, and that they aſſiſt the ordinaryes and their comiſſaries, and them fauor and maintaine as often as they or any of them to that ſhalbe required by the ſame ordinaries or theyr comiſſaries, ſo that when the ſaide officers and miniſters trauayle or ride to arreſt any lolard, or to make aſſiſtence at the inſtance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the ordinaries or their commiſſaries by vertue of this ſtatute that the ſame ordinaries and commiſſaries ſhal paye for theyr coſtes reaſonable. And that the kynges ſeruices to the which the ſame offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers be fyrſt ſworne, be preferred before al other ſtatutes for the liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:25750:12"/>of holy church, and the miniſters of the ſame, &amp; in eſpeciall for the correction and puniſhment of the heretikes and lolardes before this time made and not repelled being in their force. And alſo that al per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons conuict of hereſie, of what eſtate, condition or degre that thei be by the ſayd ordinaries or other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries left to the ſeculer power. according to the lawes of holp churche, ſhal loſe and forfeyte all theyr landes and tenementes, whiche they haue in fee ſimple in the maner as foloweth, that is to ſay, that the kinge haue al the londes and tene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, whiche the ſayde conuictes haue in fee ſimple and holden of him immediately as forfeyte, and that the other lordes, of whome the landes and tenements of ſuch conuictes be holden immediatly, after that the king is ſo ſeaced and anſwered of the yeare the day, and the waſt, haue liuery out of the kynges handes of the landes and teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes aforeſaid of them ſo holden, as it hath bene vſed in the caſe of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder of feloni, except the landes &amp; tenementes, which be holden of the ordinaries or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries, before whom any ſuch perſons im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peched of hereſie be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict, which landes &amp; tenementes, intierly ſhall remaine to the king as forfayt. And moreouer that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods &amp; cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of theſe perſons ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted, be forfeit to our ſoueraygne lorde the kinge, ſo that no perſon conuict of hereſy, &amp; left to the ſeculer power after the lawes of holy church, ſhal forfeyt his lands before that he be dead. And if any ſuch perſon ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict be enfeffed be it by fine by dede or without dede, in landes or tenementes, rentes or ſeruices in fee or otherwiſe, or hath any other poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or catels by gift or grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons to anothers vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thuſe of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uictes, that the ſame landes nor tenements, rentes nor ſeruices, nor ſuche other poſſeſſions, nor catels ſhalbe forfeit to our ſoueraign lorde the king in no wiſe. And moreouer that the iuſtices of the kings bench, &amp; iuſtices of peace, &amp; iuſtices of aſſiſe, haue ful power to enquire of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hold any errors or hereſies, as lolardes, &amp; whiche be theyr maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, receiuers, fauorers &amp; ſuſteners, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men writers of ſuch bokes, as wel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſermons, as of their ſcoles, conuenticles, congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>federaties. And that this clauſe be put in comiſſions of the iuſtices of the peace. And if any perſons be indicted of any pointes aforeſaid the ſayd iuſtices ſhal haue power to award againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>capias,</hi> &amp; the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ref ſhalbe bound to arreſt the perſon or perſons ſo endicted as ſone as he may them find by him or by his officers. And foraſmuch as the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniſance of hereſy, errors &amp; lolardries, belongeth to the iudges of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly church, &amp; not to the ſeculer Iudges, ſuche perſons iudicted ſhalbe delyuered to the ordinaries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places or to their commiſſaryes, by indentures betwixt them to be made within .x. dayes after theyr ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, orſoner yf it may be, therof to be acquit or conuict by the lawes of holy church, in caſe that theſe perſons be not indicted of another thynge, whereof the cognyſaunce belongeth to the ſeculer iudges
<pb facs="tcp:25750:12"/>and offycers, in whiche caſe, after that, that they be acquyte or dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered before the ſeculer Iudges of ſuche thinges to the ſeculer Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges helongyng, they ſhalbe ſent in ſafegarde to the ſayde ordynary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or their commiſſaryes, and to them delyuered by indentures as before, to be acquite or conuyct of ſuche lollardryes, errours, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, as is aforeſayde, after the lawes of holy churche, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the terme aforeſayde.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes that the ſayd endictementes be not taken in euidence but for information before the ſpyrytuall Iudges agaynſte ſuche perſones ſo endicted, but that the ordinaries commence theyr proceſſe agaynſt ſuch perſons endicted in the ſame maner as though no endictmeut were, hauing no regarde to ſuche endictmentes.</p>
            <p>And yf anye be endicted of hereſye, erroure, or lolardrye, and taken by the Sheriffe or other officer, he ſhalbe let to maynpryce wythin the ſayde tenne dayes by good ſuertye, for whom the ſayde ſhyreffes or other officers wil aunſwere, ſo that the ſayde perſon or perſonnes whiche were ſo endicted, be readye to be deliuered to the ſayde ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries or to theyr commiſſaries, before the ende of the ſayde tenne dayes, yf he may by anye meanes for ſicknes. And euerye ordynarye ſhal haue ſufficient commiſſaries, or commiſſary dwellyng in euerye countie in a place notable, ſo that if any ſuch perſon ſo endicted be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that the ſayde commiſſaries or commiſſarie, may be warned in the notable place where he dwelleth by the ſhyreffe, or ſome of hys officers, to come to the kynges iayle in the ſame countie, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſame perſon ſo endicted by indentures as before. And that in the inqueſte in this caſe to he taken, the ſhyreffes and other offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to whom it belongeth ſhall do to be empanelled good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient perſons, not ſuſpected nor procured, that is to ſay, that euerye of them which ſhalbe ſo empanelled in ſuche inqueſt, haue within the realme of England. C.s. of landes, tenementes, or of rente by yeare, vpon payne to loſe to the kynges vſe .x.li. and they which ſhalbe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panelled in ſuch inqueſtes in Males, euery of them ſhal haue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of .xl.s. by yeare. And yf anye ſuche perſon be arreſte, be it by the ordinary, or by the kynges officers or miniſters, and eſcape or break the priſon, before that he be acquit before the ordinarye, the goodes &amp; tattelles which he hadde the daye of ſuche arreſte, ſhalbe forfeyte to the kynge, and his landes and tenementes, whiche he had the ſame daye ſeaſed alſo into the kynges handes, the kyng ſhall haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes therof from the ſayd daye, vntyll he be yelded to the pryſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche he eſcaped. And that the foreſaid Iuſtices haue ful power to enquyre of al ſuch eſcapes, breakyng of pryſon, and alſo of landes and tenementes, goodes and cattels of ſuch perſons ſo endicted.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo that yf any ſuch perſon endicted do not retorne to the ſayd priſon and dieth not conuicte it ſhalbe lawfull to his heyres
<pb facs="tcp:25750:13"/>to enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes and tenementes of their aunceſtre. without anye other purſuyt makynge to the kyng for thys cauſe, and then al they which haue libertyes and fraunchiſes royall in England, as in the countye of Cheſter, the countye and liberty of Durham, &amp; other lyke, and alſo al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes, which haue iuriſdiction and frauchiſies royal in Wales, where the kynges wryttes do not run, haue power to execute and put in due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe articles in al poyntes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or by theyr officers, in like mauer as the Iuſtices and other the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges officers before declared ſhoulde doe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ An act that perſons dwellinge in the countrey ſhal not ſel diuers wares in eities or townes corporate by retayle.</head>
            <head type="sub">☞ The .vii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here before thys tyme the aunnent tities, horughes to wnes corporat, and maiket to wnes within thys realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, haue bene very populous, &amp; chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly inhabited with march auntes, artificers, &amp; handye craftes men, during which time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſayd cities, borowes, townes, corporat, &amp; market townes were ciuilly brought vp, and inſtructed, and alſo in the ſaid cities bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and townes corporate, kepte in good order and obeyſaunce, and the whabiters of the ſame wel ſet on worke, and kept from ydle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. By reaſon wherof the ſayde cytyes, borowes and townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, dyd then proſper in riches and great wealth, &amp; were as then not only able to ſerue and furnyſh the kynges and quenes maieſties and othere their noble progenytours kynges of thys realme, aſwell with great numbers of good able perſons, and wel furnyſhed meete for the warres, as alſo then charged, and yet chargeable with greate fee farmes, quindemes, taxes, and diuers other paymentes to the kyng and Quenes maieſties, whiche at this preſent they be not able to paye &amp; beare, but to their vtter vndoinge, beynge fewe in number to paye and bear the ſame, but alſo the ſame cytyes, boroughes, and townes corporat, are lyke to come verye ſhortly to vtter dyſtruction tuyue, and decay, by reaſon whereof the occupyers, lynnen drapers wollen drapers, haberdaſhars, and grocers, dwellynge in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries oute of the ſaide cities, boroughes, to wnes corporate, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes, do not onely occupie the art and miſtery of the ſayd ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in the places where they dwell and inhabite, but alſo come vn to the ſaid cities, boroughes, townes corporate and market townes, and there ſell theyr wares, and take away the releif of the inhabitau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the ſayd cities, borowes, to wnes corporate, and market tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to the great decaye, and vtter vndoyng of the inhabitauntes of
<pb facs="tcp:25750:13"/>the ſame, yf ſped y reformation therin be not had in time conuenient. For remedy whereof, &amp; for the better amendment of the ſayde cities, boroughes, townes corporate, and markette townes, and to thende the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, may be the better able to paye the ſaid fee farmes, and alſo to beare the other ordinary charges within the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporare, and to furnyſhe the kynge and queenes maieſtyes, with numbres of able perſons, like as they heretofore haue done in tymes paite, in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of warre.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted by our ſoueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the kyng and Quene, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parlyament aſſembled, and by thauctorytye of the ſame, that any perſon or perſons which do nowe inhabite &amp; dwel or here after ſhal inhabite or dwell in the country any wher or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in thys realme of Englande, or of anye of the ſayde cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, townes corporate, or market townes. from &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of S. Michael tharchangel next commyng, ſhall not ſell or cauſe to be fold by retayle, any wollen cloth, linnen cloth, haberdaſhe wares grocery wares, marcery wares, at or within anye of the ſayde cities. boroughes, townes corporat, or market townes, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuburbes or lybertyes of the ſayde cities, boroughes, townes corporat, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes within the ſayde realme of England (excpet it be in open fayres) vpon payne to forfeyt &amp; loſe for euerye tyme ſo offendyng the ſume of .vi.s.viii.d. &amp; the whole wares ſo ſolde, profered and offered to be ſolde, contrarye to the forme, entente and effect of thys preſent acte, as aboue is ſayde, the one moyte of all whyche forfeytures to be to the vſe of oure ſayde ſoueraygne lorde and ladye the kynge and queenes maieſties, and the other halfe to hym or them that ſhal ſeaſe and ſue for the ſame in anye of the kynge and queenes courtes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, by byll plant, action of debt, inſormation or otherwyſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no eſſoyne, proteccion or wager of lawe ſhalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this act ſhall not in any wyſe extende, nor be hurtful to anye perſon or perſons, that bryng any of the ſayd wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len cloth, linen cloth, haberdaſhe grocerye, mercery, ware or wares to anye of the ſayde cities, boroughes, townes corporate, or markette townes to be ſolde, or cauſe to be ſolde, by whole ſale, in groſſe and not by retayle, but they and euery of them maye laufully ſel the ſame in as large and ample maner, forme, and condition by whole ſale in groſſe &amp; not by retayle, as they and euerye of them myght haue done at any tyme or tymes, before the makyng of thys acte. Anye thynge herein to the contrary not withſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway that thys preſent acte ſhall not extende to any perſon or perſons, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now dwelor inhabyte in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, or herafter
<pb facs="tcp:25750:14"/>ſhal dwel or inhabit out of any of the ſayd cities, borowes, to wnes corporate, or markete townes, but that theye, and cuerye of them at any tyme hereafter, when they or any of them ſhalbe free of any the guyldes, &amp; liberties, of any the ſaid cities, borowes, to wnes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porat, or market towns, and dwel or inhabite wichin any of the ſame cities, borowes, townes coruorate, or markette townes, that they and euerye of them ſo veyng free, ſhal and may ſel or cauſe to be ſolde any of the wares aforeſayd, by retayle in as ample and large maner as they and enerye of them might haue done, beyng free of the ſayde cities, borowes, and townes aforeſayde, before the makyng of thys act. Any clauſe or article in thys act to the contrarye notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritye aforeſaid that it ſhalbe laweful to al perſonnes, to ſell or cauſe to beſolde by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle or otherwyſe, al maner of cloth, lynnen or wollen of their owne makyng in euery city, boronghe, towne corporat and market towne within the realme, as frelye and franklye as they might haue done before the making of thys acte. Anye thynge in the ſame conteyned to the contrarye hereof not withſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway that thys act or any thinge therein conteyned ſhal not be prciudirial or hurtefull to the liberties, and prtuileges of the vniuerſities of Cambridge and Oxford, or eyther of them. Anye thing in this acte heretofore mencioned to the contrarye notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ An arte repealynge all Statutes, articles, and prouiſions made agaynſt the Sea Apoſtolike of Rome, ſynce the .xx. yeare of kyng Henry the eyghte, and alſo for the eſtabliſhmente of all ſpirituall and eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentes conueyed to the laytie.</head>
            <head type="sub">The eyght Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as ſynce the .xx. yeare of kynge Henry theyghte of famous memory, father vnto youre maieſtie, oure moſt naturall ſoueraygne, and gratious Ladye and Queene, muche ſalſe and erronious doctryne, hath bene taught, preached, and written partly by diuers the hatural borne ſubiectes of this realme and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beynge brought in he ther from fondrye other forreyne countreyes hath bene ſowen &amp; ſpred abroad within the ſame. By reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of al wel the ſpiritualtie as the temporaltie of your highnes realmes and dominions haue fwerned from the obedience of the ſea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, and declyned from the vnitie of Chriſtes churche, and ſo haue
<pb facs="tcp:25750:14"/>continued vntyl ſuche time as your maieſtie beyngfyrſt reyſed vp by God, and ſet in the ſeate Royall ouer vs. and then by his deuine and gratious prouidence knit in mariage with the moſte noble and ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous prynce, the king our ſoueraigne lorde your huſbande the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes holines and the Sea apoſtolike ſent hither vnto your maieſties (as vnto perſons vndefried, &amp; by gods goodnes preſerued frome the common infection aforeſayd) and to the whole realnie, the mooſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerende father in God, the Lorde Cardinall Poole, Legate de late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, to cal vs home agayne into the ryght way, from whence we haue al this longe while wandred and ſtrayed abroade. And we after ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry longe, and greuous plagues and calamities, ſeynge by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God our owne exrours, haue knowledged the ſame vnto the ſayde mooſt reuerende father, and by hym haue bene, and are the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the contemplation of your maieſties, receyued and embraced into the vnitie and boſome of Chriſtes church, and vpon our humble ſubmiſſion and promiſe made for a declaration of our repentaunce. to repeale and abrogate ſuche actes and ſtatutes as had bene made in parlyament ſynce the ſayd .xx. yeare of the ſayd kynge Henrye the ryght, againſt the ſupremacy of the Sea apoſtolike, as in our ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion exhibited to the ſayd moſte reuerende father in God, by youre maieſties appeareth. The renor wherof enſueth.</p>
            <p>We the lordes ſpititual and remporall, and the commons aſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this preſent parlyament, repreſentyng the whole body of the realme of Englande, and the dominions of the ſame, in the name of our ſelues perticulerly and alſo of the ſayde body vniuerſallye in this our ſupplication directed to your maieſties with moſt humble ſuyte that it may by youre graces interceſſion &amp; meane be exhibited to the mooſte renerende father in God, the ſorde cardynall Poole legate. ſent ſpetiallye hyther from our mooſte holye father pope Iuly the thyrd, and the Sea apoſtolyke of Rome, do declare our ſelues very fory and repentaunte, of the feiſme and diſobedience, committed in thys realme &amp; dominions aforeſaid againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Sea of apoſtolike eyther by making, agreing, or executing any lawes, ordinaunces, or commaunde mentes agaynſt the ſuprentacye of the ſayd ſea, or other wyſe doyng or ſpeakyng, that myght impugne the fame: offerynge our ſelues, &amp; promiſing by thys our ſupplication, that for a token and knowledge of our ſayd repentaunce, we be and ſhalbe alwayes redy vnder and with thauctorities of your maieſties, to the vtter moſt of our poweres, to do that ſhall lye in vs, for the abrogation and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the ſayde lawes and ordinaunces in thys preſent parlyament aſwell for our ſelues as for the whole bodye, whome we repreſente, whervpon we mooſt humblye deſyer your maieſtyes as perſonages vndefiled in offence of hys bodye towardes the ſayd Sea, whych neuertheles god by hys prouydence, hath made ſubiect to you, ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:25750:15"/>ſet forth this our moſt humble ſuyte, that we maye obtayne from the Sea apoſtolike, by the ſayde mooſt reuerend father, as well perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerly, as generally, abſolution, releaſe, and diſcharge, from all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuche cenſures, and ſentences, as by the lawes of the churche we be fallen into. And that we may as children repentaunte, be recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued into the boſome and vnitie of Chriſtes churche, ſo as this noble realme with al the membres thereof, may in this vnitie, and periecte obedience to the Sea apoſtolyke, and Popes, for the tyme veynge, ſerue god and your maieſties, to the furtherance and aduaimceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his honor and glorye. We are at the interceſſion of your maieſtyes by thauctoritie of oure holye father Pope Iuly the thyrde, and of the Sea apoſtolike, aſſoiled, diſcharged, and deliuered from excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, interdictions and other cenſures eccleſiaſticall, which hath hanged ouer oure heades for oure ſayde defaultes ſynce the tyme of the ſayde ſchiſme mentioned in our ſupplication. The whiche tyme the ſayde lorde Legate and we do all declare, recognyſe, and meane by thys act to be onely ſince the .xx. yeare of the raigne of your mooſt noble father kyng Henry the eyght. It maye nowe lyke your maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, that for the accompliſhment of oure promyſe made in the ſayde ſupplication, that is, to repeale all lawes &amp; ſtatutes made contrarye to the ſayde ſupremacy and Sea apoſtolyke, duryng the ſayd ſciſme, the whiche is to be vnderſtande, ſynce the .xx. yeare of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, and ſo the ſayd lorde Legate doth accept and recogniſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Where in the parliament begonne and holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxi. yeare of the raygne of the late kynge of moſt famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kyng Henry theyght, one act was then and there made agaynſte pluralities of benefices, for takynge of farmes by ſpyritual men and for none reſidence, in the which act amongeſte other thynges it was ordeyned and enacted that yf any perſon or perſons, at any tyme af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fyrſt day of Apryll in the yeare of our Lorde God a thouſand fyue hundred and thyrtye contrary to the ſame acte, ſhoulde procure and obteyne at the courte of Rome, or els where anye lycence or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, vnion, tolleration, or diſpenſatyon, to receaue or take anye more benefices with cure, then was limitted and appoynted by the ſame acte, or els at any tyme after the ſayde daye ſhoulde put inexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution any ſuche licence, tolleration, or diſpenſation, before that time obteyned contrarye to the ſayde acte, that then euery ſuche perſon or perſons ſo after the ſayd day, ſuyng for hym ſelfe, or receauynge, and takyng ſuche benefice by force of ſuche lycence or lycences, vnion, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, or diſpenſation, that is to ſaye, the ſame perſon or perſonnes onely, and no nother, ſhould for euery ſuch defaulte, incurre the daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, payne and penaltie of, xx.li. ſterl. and ſhoulde alſo looſe the whole profites of euerye ſuche benefice or benefices, as he receaueth, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:25750:15"/>by force of any ſuch licence or licences, vnion, tolleration, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. And where alſo in the ſayd acte it was ordeyned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that yf any perſon or perſons dydde procure, or obteyne at the courte of Rome, or els where anye maner of lycence or diſpenſation to be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at their dignities, prebend, or benefices, contrary to the ſayd acte, that then euery ſuche perſon or perſonnes puttynge in execution anye ſuch diſpenſation, or licence for him ſelfe frome the ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fyrſt daye of Apryll, in the ſayde yeare of our Lord God, a M. ſyue hundred and thirtye, woulde runne and incurre in the peualtye damage, and payne of .xx.li. ſter. for euerye tyme ſo doynge to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyted and recouered, as by the ſayd act is declared. And yet ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence or diſpenſation ſo procured, or to be putte in execution, to bee boyde and of none effecte, as by the ſame acte more playnelye it doth and may appeare.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parlyament, that as muche only of the ſayde aete, as concerneth the articles and clauſes aforeſayd, and al and euery the wordes and ſentences conteyned in the ſayd act, concernyngs the ſayde articles and clauſes, and euerye of them ſhal from henceforth be repealed, adnulled, reuoked adnihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and vtterly made voyde for euer. Any thinge in the ſayde acte to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandynge.</p>
            <p>And where alſo at the ſeſſion of the ſame parliament holden vpon prorogation, in the .xxiii. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry theyght, one act intituled: the act that no perſon ſhalbe cyted out of the dioceſſe where he or ſhe dwelleth, except in certayne caces And where alſo at the ſayd parliament, in the ſeſſion holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter vpon prorogation the .xxiiii. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kyng Henry theyght, one act was made that appeales in ſuche caſes as hath ben vſed to be puriued to the ſea of Rome, ſhoulde not from he free forth be had nor vſed but within this realme. And where alſo at the ſayd parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxi. yere of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry the eighte, and there conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by diners prorogations vnty the .xxiiii. daye of Apryll, in the xxvii. yere of his raigne, one act was made concerninge reſtrayntes of paymentes of annaties, and firſte fruites of archebyſhopryckes, and byſhopryckes of the Sea of Rome. And where at a Seſſion of the ſayde parlyament, holden in the .xxv. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kyng, there was alſo one acte made, intituled, the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the clergye to the kynges mateſtyes, and one other art entitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, one acte reſtraynynge, the ſayde paymentes of annaces, or lyrſte frutes to the byſhop of Rome, and of the electyng and couſecratyng of the arch byſhoppes and byſhoppes wythin thys reaime. And one other act was then and there made entituled: an act concernyng the exoneration of the kynges ſubiectes, from exactyons &amp; impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tons
<pb facs="tcp:25750:16"/>before that time payed to the Sea of Rome, and for hauing licences and diſpenſations within this realme, withoute ſuynge further for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parliamente, that the ſayde ſeuerall actes made for the reſtraynt of paymente of the fayde annates, and fyrſte fruites, and all other the ſayde actes made in the ſayd .xxiiii. and .xxv. yeres of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge, and euery of them, and al and euery braunch, article, matter, and ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in them, and euerye of them conteyned, ſhalbe by auctorytye of thys preſent parliament from hence forth vtterly voyde, made fruſtrate and repealed, to al intentes, conſtructions and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctority of thys preſente parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that al and euery theſe actes folowynge. That is to ſaye, one act made at the ſeſſion of the ſayd parliament holden vpon proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Weſt. in the .xxvi. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry theyght, entituled an acte, concerning the kinges highnes to be ſupreme head of the church of Englande, and to haue auctorytye to reforme and redreſſe al errours, hereſies, and abuſes in the ſame And one other acte made in the ſame ſeſſion of the ſame parliamente entituled, an acte for nomination and conſecration of Suffraganes within this realme. And one other acte made in the .xxvii. yeare of the raigne of the ſayd late kyng Henry the eighte, entituled, an acte wherby the kynge ſhoulde haue power to nominate .xxxii. perſones of his Clergy and Laye fee for the makynge of Eccleſticall lawes. An alſo one other act, made at the parliamente holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the .xxviii. yere of the raygne of the ſayd late kynge Henry the eyghte entituled, an acte extinguiſhinge the auctorytye of the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome. And one other act made in the ſame parlyament, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, an acte for the releaſe of ſuche as then had obteyned preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded licences, and diſpenſations from the Sea of Rome. And alſo all that parte of the acte, made in the ſayde .xxviii. yeare of the ſayde kynge, entituled, an acte for the eſtabliſhemente of the Succeſſion of the imperiall crowne of the realme, that concerneth a prohibition to marry within the degrees expreſſed in the ſayde acte. And alſo one other acte made at the parliamente holden at Weſtminſter, in the xxxi. yeare of the raygue of the ſayde late kynge Henrye the eyghte, entituled, an acte auctoryſynge the kynges hyghnes to make byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes by his letters patentes. And one other acte made in the ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame parliament begon in the ſayd .xxx. yeare, holden vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prorogation, the .xxxii. yeare of the reigne of the ſayde kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eyghte, entituled, and acte concerninge precontractes of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyages, and touching degrees of conſangumitie. And one other act made in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxv. yeare of the reygne of the ſayd late king Henry theyght, entituled, an acte for
<pb facs="tcp:25750:16"/>the ratificatyon of the kings maieſties ſtile, ſhal henceforth be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, made fruſtrate, voyde, and of none effect. And where alſo at the fayd parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxxv. yere of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, one othere act was made enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teled: an act concernyng the ſtabliſhment of the ſucceſſion of the ſayd king in the imperiall crowne of this realme. In the which act there is a forme of a corporall othe deuiſed and ſete furth, that euerye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of this realme ſhould be bounde to take agaynſt the power, auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie and iuriſdictyon of the ſea of Rome. Be it enacted by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this prefent parlyament that ſo muche of the ſayde acte as toucheth the ſayde oth againſt the ſupremacy, and al othes therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had, made, &amp; geuen ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voyde repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and of none effect. And wher alſo one other act was made in the xxxvii. yere of the raigne of the ſayde late king Henrye theyght enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled an act that doctours of the cyuyl law, being maried might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reciſe eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction. Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parlyament, that the ſayde act laſt before mentioned, and all and euerye braunche, article, ſentence and matter, conceyned in the ſame, ſhal from henſeforth be repealed, and vtterly made voyd, and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>And where one other act was made at the fyrſt yere of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, holden at Weſtminſter, in the fyrſt yere of the rayne of kyng Edwarde the ſyxt, entituled an act for the repeale of certayne Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, concerning treaſons, fellonies. &amp;c In the which act amongeſt other thyngs ther is conteyned certeyne prouyſyons, paynes, penal tyes, and forfeytures for and agaynſt ſuche, as ſhould by open preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges, expres wordes, ſayinges, wrytynge, pryntynge ouert dede, oracte affirme, or ſet furth that the kyng of thys realme, for tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, is not or ought not to be ſupreame head in earth, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches of England and Ireland, ne of anye of them, or that the byſhoppe of Rome or any other perſonne or perſons, other then the kyng of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land for the tyme beyng, is or ought to be ſupreame heade of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame churches, or any of them, as in the ſame act laſt before rehearſed, and at large is conteyned and maye appeare. Be it enacted by auctority of this preſent parlyament, that theſe clauſes before rehearſed, and other of the ſayde act, conceruyng the ſupremacy, and all and euerye braunche, artycle, wordes, and ſentence in the ſame ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the derogatyon of the ſupremacy of the popes holynes, or the ſea of Rome, and al paynes, penalties, &amp; forfeytures, made agaynſt them that ſhould by any meanes ſet furth, or extol the ſayd ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voyde and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoryty aforeſayd, that al clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſentences, and articles of euerye other ſtatute, or acte of Parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made ſithence the ſayde .xx. yeare of the raygne of kyng Henry
<pb facs="tcp:25750:17"/>theyght, agaynſte the ſupreame auctoritie of the Popes holynes, or Sea apoſtolike of Rome, or conteining any other matter of the ſame affect only, that is repealed in any of the Statutes aforeſayde, ſhalbe alſo by auctoritie hereof from henceforth vtterly voyd, fruſtrate and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>And where we your moſt humble ſubiectes, the lordes ſpyrytual and temporall, and commons in this preſent parliamente aſſembled, haue exhibited to youre maieſties one other ſupplycation in fourme folowing.</p>
            <p>We the lordes ſpyritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled repreſentinge the whole bodye of this realme, reduced and receiued by your maieſties interceſſion to the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Chriſtes churche, and the obedience of the Sea apoſtolike of Rome, and the Popes holynes gouerning the ſame, make moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſuite vnto your maieſties, to be likewiſe meanes and interceſſors that all occaſions of contention, hatred, grudge, ſuſpition, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both outwardly and inwardly in mens conſciences, which might ariſe amongeſt vs, by reaſon of diſobedience, may by auctoritie of the Popes holines, and by miniſtration of the ſame vnto vs, by the moſt reuerend father in god, the lord Cardinal Poole, by diſpenſation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration or permiſſion reſpectiuely, as the caſe ſhal requyre, be aboly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and taken away, and by aucthoritie ſufficient theſe articles folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyng, and generally all others, when anye occaſion ſhall ſo requyre may be prouided for, and confyrmed.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt that al byſhoprickes, cathedrall Churches, hoſpitales, colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſcholes, and other ſuch foundations nowe continuing, made by auctoritye of parlyament, or otherwiſe eſtabliſhed, accordinge to the order of the lawes of this realme, ſithence this ſchiſme may be confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med and continued for euer.</p>
            <p>Item that mariages made <hi>infra gradus prohibites conſanguinitatis, affinitatis cognationis ſpiritualis,</hi> or whiche might be made voyd <hi>propter impedimentum pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bonestatis iuſtitiae,</hi> or for any other cauſe prohibited by the canons only may be confirmed, and children borne of thoſe mariages declared le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittimate, ſo as thoſe mariages were made accordinge to the lawes of the realme for the tyme beinge, and be not directelye agaynſte the lawes of God, nor in ſuch caſe as the Sea apoſtolyke hath not vſed to diſpence withal.</p>
            <p>That inſtitutions of benefices, and other promotions eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and diſpenſations made according to the forme of the act of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, may be lykewyſe confyrmed.</p>
            <p>That all iudiciall proceſſes, made before anye ordinaries of thys realme, or before any delegates vpon any apeales, according to thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the lawes of the realme, may be likewiſe ratified &amp; confirmed And finallye where certayne actes and ſtatutes haue bene made in
<pb facs="tcp:25750:17"/>the tyme of the late ſciſme, concernyng the landes, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Archbyſſhopryckes, and Byſſhopryckes, the ſuppreſſion, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of monaſteries, Abbeyes, pryoryes, chauntries, colleges, &amp; al other the goodes and cattels of religious houſes. Synce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che tyme, the ryght and dominion of certaine landes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, goodes, and catteles, belongynge to the ſame, be dyſperſed abroade, &amp; come to the handes, and poſſeſſions of diuerſe and ſondry perſons, who by gyfte, purchaſe, exchaunge, &amp; other meanes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the order of the lawes and ſtatutes of thys Realme, for the tyme beynge haue the ſame. For the auoydynge of all ſcruples that might growe by any thoccaſions aforeſayd, or by any other waies, or meanes, whatſoeuer: It may pleaſe youre maieſties, to be interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and mediatours, to the ſayd mooſte reuerend father, Cardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Pole, that all ſuche cauſes, and quarels as by pretence of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayde ſcyme, or by any other occation, or meane whatſoeuer, might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Popes holynes, or Sea Apoſtolyke, or by any other iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Eccleſiaſticall, maye be vtterly remoued, and taken awaye ſo as all perſons hauing ſufficient conueyaunce of the ſayd landes, and hereditamentes, goodes and cattels, as is aforeſayd, by the common lawes actes, or Statutes of this realme, may without ſcruple of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyence, enioye them withoute impechmente or trouble by pretence of anye generall counſayle, Canons, or Eccleſſaſtical lawes, &amp; cleare from al daungers of the cenſures of the Churche.</p>
            <p>And comformably herevnto, the Byſſhoppes and Cleargy of the prouynce of Catorbury haue preſented to your maieſties a ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this tenour that foloweth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>Nos Epiſcopi &amp; clerus Cantuarienſis prouinciae in hac Synodo more noſtro ſolito, dum Regni parliamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celebratur, congregati, cum omni debita humilitate &amp; reuerentia, exponimus Maieſtatibus ueſtris, quod licet Eccleſiarum, quibus in Epiſcopos, Decanos, Archidiaconos, rectores, &amp; uicarios praefecti ſumus, &amp; animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quae &amp; nobis curae noſtrae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectae ſunt &amp; earundem bonorum iuriſdictionum, &amp; iurium, ex ſacrorum Canonum diſpoſitione, defenſores, &amp; curatores conſtituti ſumus &amp; prop teria ipſarum bona iuriſdictionis, &amp; iura in pernicioſo huius Regni prae terito ſciſmate deperdita &amp; amiſſa, omni ſtudio, &amp; totis noſtris uiribus recuperare &amp; ad priſtinum Eccleſiarum ius reuocare, iuris remedijs niti deberemus: Nichilominus tamen habito prius per nos ſuper hac re maturo Conſilio, et deliberatione ingenue fatemur; nos optime cognoſſere, quam haec bonorum Eccleſiaſticorum difficilis &amp; quaſi impoſſibilis eſſet recupe ratio propter multiplices ac pene inextricabiles ſuper hijs habitos contrac<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:25750:18"/>ſitiones &amp; quod ſi ea tentaretur, quies et tranquillitas Regni facile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutbaretur, &amp; unitas Eecleſiae Catholicae, quae iam pietate, &amp; aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Maieſtatum ueſtrum hoc in regno introducta eſt, cum maxima dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultate ſuum debitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> progreſſive, &amp; ſinem ſortiri poſſet. Ideo nos bonum &amp; quietem publicam priuatis commoditatibus, &amp; ſalutem tot animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praetioſo Chriſti ſanguine redemptarum terrenis bonis anteponentes, &amp; non quae noſtra, ſed quae Ieſu Chriſti ſunt quaerentes, Maieſtates ueſtras enixe rogamus, eiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> humiliter ſupplicamus, ut reuerendiſſimo in Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to patri, domino Reginaldo Cardinali Polo, ad ipſas, &amp; uniuerſum hoc Anglie regnum ſanctiſſimi domini noſtri, Domini Iulij, Papae tertij, &amp; Apoſtolicae ſedis de latere legato, haec nomine noſtro inſinuari, &amp; apud eum intercedere dignentur, ut in hiis bonis Eccleſiaſtiſis in parte, uel in to to arbitrio ſuo iuxta facultates ſibi ab eodem ſanctiſſimo domino uoſtro Papa conceſſas eorundem bonorum detentoribus elargiendes et relaxan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis publicum bonum priuato pacem et tranquillitatem diſsidijs, &amp; per tur bationibus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animarum ſalutem bonis terrenis preferre, &amp; ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere uelit. Nos enim in omnibus quae ab ipſo legato ſtatuta, et ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta circa haec bona fuerint exnunc, prout extunc, et econtra conſenſum noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum preſtamus, imo etiam ut in premiſſis ſe difficilem aut reſtrictum red dere non uelit, maieſtates ueſtrae noſtro nomine eum hortari, &amp; rogare dignabuntur. In ſuper maieſtatibus ueſtris ſupplicamus ut pro ſua pietate efficere dignentur, ut ea quae adiuriſdictionem noſtram et libertatem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticam pertinent, ſine quibus debitum noſtri paſtoralis officij et cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae animarum nobis commiſſae exercere non poſſumus, uobis ſuperiorum temporum iniuria ablata reſtituantur, et ea nobis, et Eccleſij perpetuo il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſa et ſalua permaneant, et ut omnes leges, quae hanc noſtram iuriſdictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; libertatem Eccleſiaſticam tollunt, ſeu quouis modo impediunt, abrogentur ad honorum dei, et maieſtatum ueſtrarum, et uniuerſi huius Regni Spirituale, et temporale, commodum, &amp; ſalutem, certam ſpem eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am habentes, Maieſtates ueſtras, pro ſua ſingulari in ipſum deum pietate pro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> multis et in ſignibus ab ipſius dei bonitate acceptis beneficijs neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatibus, &amp; in commodis huius ſui Regni Eccleſiarum maxime curam am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum habentium nunquam defuturas eſſe, ſed prout opus fuerit, conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuras at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> prouiſuras.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Foraſmuch as the ſayde mooſte reuerende father, the Lorde Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, at the interceſſion of your maieſties hath by thauctoritie of the Sea Apoſtolike, ſufficiently diſpenſed in the matters ſpecifyed in the ſayd ſeueral ſupplications, as in his ſayd letters of diſpenſatyon is conteyned more at large. The tenor wherof enſueth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:18"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>Reginaldus miſeratione d uina Sanctae Mariae in Coſmodin Sanctae Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manae Eccleſiae, Diaconis, Cardinalis Polus nuncupatus, ad Sereniſſimos Philippum &amp; Mariam, Angliae, Reges, fidei defenſores, et umuerſum An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliae regnum, Sanctiſſimi Domini noſtri Papae, et ſedes Apoſtolicae de la tere legatus eiſdem Sereniſſimis Philippo et Mariae Regibus ſalutem in Domino ſempiternam. Cum ſupremum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilium iſtius Regni parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nuncupatum Maieſtatibus ueſtris, per ſuos ſupplices libellos expoſuiſſet quod perniciociſſimo ſciſmate, in hoc regno alias uigente, quod nunc dei miſericordia, &amp; maieſtatum ueſtrarum pietate extinctum eſt, aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ipſius parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, non nulli Epiſcopatus diuiſi, &amp; ex his aliquae infe riores Eccleſiae, in cathedrales ereſtae, et ſcolae, atque hoſpitalia fundata nec non plurimae diſpenſationes et beneficiorum prouiſiones factae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ac multae perſonae quibus perſuaſum fuerat, luris Canonici diſpoſitiones hoc in Regno amplius locum non habere, inter ſe in gradibus conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis uel affinitatis de iure prohibitis, &amp; alijs impedimentis Canonicis ſibi obſtantibus matrimonia, per uerba de preſenti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traxerunt, et multis actus iudiciarij, &amp; proceſſus, tam in primis, quam ulterioribus inſtantijs ſuper rebus ſpiritualibus, &amp; Eccleſiaſticis coram iudicibus tam Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs quam delegatis, qui aucthoritate laicali procedebant, habiti &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, ad ſuper eis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae latae, et promulgatae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et bona eccleſiaſtica per diuerſas eiuſdem regni perſonas occupata, et apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa fuerunt. Quae quidem licet ex ſacrorum Canonum inſtitutis irrita declarari poſſent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſi ad alium ſtatum, quam in quo nunc ſunt, reuocarentur, publica pax &amp; quis uniuerſi regni turbaretur, et maxima confuſio orietur, perſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſi dictorum bonorum poſſeſſoresmoleſtarentur, et proptere amaieſtati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus ueſtris humiliter ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere digne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ut premiſſarum rerum firmitari, et ſtabilitati, et ſimul huius Regni quieti, et tranquillitati de benignitate Apoſtolica prouidere uelimus. Cunque Epiſcopi quoque deinde, ac reliquus prouinciae Catuarienſis Clerus totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fere corpus Eccleſiaſticorum regni repreſentus, ad quos haec bonorum Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſticorum cauſa maxime pertin et, expoſuerint, quod haec bona adius eccleſiarum reuocare no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quin pax vniuerſalis, &amp; quies huius reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni turbetur, et cauſa fidei at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> unitatis Eccleſiae, iam tota omnium conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu hoc in regno in troducta, in maximum periculum adducatur, et propte reaipſi quoque ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere uelint, ut in his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis Eccleſiaſticis poſſeſsoribus relaxandus reſtricti et difficilis eſſe nolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, maieſtatis autem ueſtrae, ad quas maxime ſpectat prouidere ut regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſtari regimini et curae commiſſum in pace et tranquillitate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruetur.
<pb facs="tcp:25750:19"/>His ſupplicationibus et poſtulatis cognitis et mature conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis iudicauerit ea omnia, et maxime illa, quae in bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſtitorum cauſa petuntur, pro cauſa fidei et pro pace publica, per nos de bere ſine ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la dilatione concedi, et que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rogatae fuerunt, apud nos intercedere dignatae fuerint, pro ut in ſupplicationibus per idem ſupremu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos ac clerum praefatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maieſtatibus ueſtris porrectis, atque in libello interceſſiones per eaſdem maieſtates ueſtras nobis ſimul cum alijs ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationibus exhibito, latius apparet. Id circo nos qui ad maieſtates ueſtras et hoc uobiliſſimum ueſtrum regnum a Sanctiſſimo Domino noſtro Iulio Papa tertio ipſius et ſedis Apoſtolicae de latere legati miſſi ſumus, ut regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſtud, quod iam diu ab eccleſiae Catholicae unitate ſeparatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuerat. Deo et Eccleſia Chriſti, eiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in terris uicario reconciliaremus: et ut ea omnia quae ad pace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et tranquillitatem huius regni pertinere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, omni ſtudio procuraremus, poſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei benignitate, et maieſtatem ueſtraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pietate, per authoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eiuſdem Sanctiſſimi Domini noſtri Papae, cuius uices hic ſuſtinemus, reconciliatio iam facta eſt, ut paci et tranquillitati regni prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fati conſulamus, atque ut unitas eccleſiae, ex qua ſalus tot animarum prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cioſo Chriſti ſanguine redemptarum dependet, hoc in regno iam introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta corrobaretur, &amp; ſalua permaneat, cum utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rei ſtabilitatem in eo maxime conſiſtere, ſi horum Eccleſiaſticorum bonorum poſſeſſoribus mo leſtia nulla in feratur quo nimus ea teneant, tot et tam grauia teſtimonia nobis fidem faciant, et maieſtatum ueſtrarum interceſſio, quaepro unitate Eccleſiae, et ſedis Apoſtolicae auctoritate hoc in regno inſtauranda tam ſtudioſe, et tam pia elaborarunt, eam quam par eſt auctoritatem apud nos habeat, et ut uniuerſum hoc regnum ſedis Apoſtolicae maternam uere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et charitatem erga ſe agnoſcat, et re ipſa experiatur: quoſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad quos infra ſcripta pertinent, a quibuſuis excommunicationis, ſuſpenſio nis, et interdicti, alijs<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eccleſiaſticis ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenſiis, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuris et paenis a iure uel ab homine quauis occaſione uel cauſa latis, ſi quibus quomodo libet innodati exiſtunt, ad effectum preſentium dum taxat conſequendum harum ſerie abſoluentes, et abſolutos fore cenſentes, aucthoritate Apoſtolica, per litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Sanctiſſimi domini noſtri, domini Iulij Papae tertij nobis conceſſa, &amp; qua fungimur in haec parte, tenore praeſentium diſpenſamus, quod omnes et ſingulae Cathedralium Eccleſiarum erectiones, hoſpitalium, et ſcolaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fundationes tempore praeteriti ſciſmatis, licet de facto et nullituratte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatae ineo ſtatu, in quo nunc ſunt, perpetuo firmae et ſtabilis parmaneant, illiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Apoſtolicae firmitatis robur adijcimus, ita ut non ea aucthoritate, qua prius, ſed ea quam nunc eis tribuimus, factae ab omnibus cenſeantur, &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:25750:19"/>omnibus et ſingulis perſonis regni predicti, quae in aliquo conſanguinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis uel aſſinitatis gradu etiam multiplici, uel cognationis ſpiritualie, ſeu publicae honeſtatis iuſticiae impedimento de iure poſitiuo introductis, &amp; in quibus ſanctiſſimus dominus noſter Papa diſpenſare conſueuit matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia ſcienter uel ignorantur de facto contraxerint ut alique impedimen torum premiſſorum, non obſtante in eorum matrimonijs, ſic contractis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere &amp; licite remanere, ſeu illa de nouocontrahere poſſint, miſſericorditer in domino diſpenſamus, prolem ſuſceptam, ſuſcipiendam ligitimam, de cernentes, ita tamen ut qui ſcienter et malitioſe contraxerint, a ſententia exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municationis, et ab inceſtus ſeu ſacrilegij reatu, abſolutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſuo ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nario, uel curato, quibus id faciendi facultatem conſedimus, obtineant, ac omnes Eccleſiaſticas ſeculares, ſeu quorumuis ordinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regulares perſonas quae aliquas impetrationes, diſpenſationes, conceſſiones, gratias et indulta tam Ordines, quam beneficia Eccleſiaſtica, ſeu alias ſpirituales materias praetenſa aucthoritate ſupremitatis Eccleſiae Anglicanae licet nulliter et de facto obtinuerint, et ad cor reuerſae Eccleſia unitati reſtitutae fuerint, in ſuis Ordinibus, &amp; beneficijs per nos ipſos, ſeu a nobis ad id deputatos, miſericorditer recipiemus, pro ut iam multae receptae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuper his opportune in Domino diſpenſabimus: Ac omnes proceſſus inquibuſuis inſtantijs coram quibuſuis iudicibus, tam ordinariis quam diligatis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laicis ſuper materijs ſpiritualibus habitos &amp; formatos, &amp; ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tias ſuper eis latas, licet nulliter et de facto, quo ad nullitatem ex defectu iuriſdictio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis praefato tantum in ſurgentem ſanamus, illoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, et illas aucthoritie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolica confirmamus: Ac quibuſuis huius regni perſonis, ad quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma nus bona Eccleſiaſtica ex quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> contractu ſeu titulo onoroſo uel lucra tiuo iam deuenerint, illaque tenuerint, ſeu etiam teneant, omnes, &amp; quos cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fructus ex eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonis, licet indebite perceptos, in tote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remittimus &amp; relaxamus. Volentes ad decernentes, quod dictorum bonorum Eccleſi aſticorum tam mobilium quam immobilium poſſeſſores preſatino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſint in preſenti nec in poſterum, ſeu per conſiliorum generalium, uel prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialium diſpoſitiones, ſeu decretales Romanorum pontificum Epiſtolas, ſeu aliam quamcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cenſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſtica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dictis bonis ſeu eorunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſione moleſtari, inquietari, uel perturbari, nec eis aliquae ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſurae uel pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae eccleſiaſticae propter huiuſmodi detentionem, ſeu non reſtitutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> irro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari uel inſligi, &amp; ſic per quoſcunque iudices, &amp; auditores ſublata eis qua ſuis aliter iudicandi et interpretandi facultate, et auctoritate iudicari et diffinire debere, &amp; quicquid ſecus attemptari contigerit, irritum et inane fore decernimus, non obſtantibus praemiſſis defectibus, &amp; quibuſui:
<pb facs="tcp:25750:20"/>Apoſtolicis, ac in prouincialibus, et ſinodalibus concilijs editis, ſpeciali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus uel generablibus conſtitionis, &amp; ordinationibus, caeteriſque contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs quibuſcunque. Admonemus tamen cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuiſo Epiſcopatum, &amp; erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Cathedralium Eccleſiarum ſint de maioribus cauſis, quae ſummo ponti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fici ſunt reſeruatae recurrendum eſse ad ſuam ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctitatem, &amp; ab eaſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer poſtu andum, ut haec confirmare, ſeu de nouo facere dignetur. Et licet omnes res mobiles Eccleſiarum indiſtincte ijs, qui eos tenent lelax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auerimus, eos tamen admonitos eſſe uolumus, ut aut oculos habentes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utni iudicij ſeueritatem contra Balthaſarem Regem Babilonis, qui ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſacra non a ſe, ſed a patre e templo ablata in prophanos uſus conuertit ea proprijs Eccleſiis ſi extant, uel aliis reſtituant. Hortantes etiam, &amp; per uiſera miſericordiae Ieſu Chriſti obteſtantes eos omnes, quos haecres tangit, ut ſalutis ſuae non omnino immemores, hoc ſaltem efficiant, ut ex bonis Eccleſiaſlicis, maxime ijs, quae ratione perſonatuum et uicariatuum populi miniſtrorum ſuſtentatio fuerint ſpeſi aliter deſtinata, ſeu alijs Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedralibus, &amp; alijs quae nunc extant, inferioribus Eccleſijs curam anima rum exercentibus ita prouideatur, ut earu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſtores, perſonae et uicarii co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode, &amp; honoſte iuxta eorum qualitatem, &amp; ſtatum ſuſtentari poſſint, &amp; curam animarum laudibiliter exercere, &amp; onera incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bentia congrue ſupportare Datum Lambeth prope Londinum VVintonien<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dioceſſ. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Natiuitatis domini Milleſimo, quingenteſimo, quinquageſimo quarto Nono Cal. Ianuarij Pontif. Sactiſſimi in Chriſto patris, &amp; Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, Donini, Inlij diuina prouidentia Papae tertij. Anno quinto.</p>
                  <p>Reginaldus Cardinalis Polus Legatus</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We the ſayd lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and commons in this preſent parlyament aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled, rendring moſt humble thankes to you: maieſties, by whoſe interceſſion and meanes we haue obteyned the ſayd dyſpenſations of the popes holynes by the ſayd moſt reuerend father in god, his legare, moſt humbly beſecheth the ſame, that it may be ordeined as foloweth.</p>
            <p>And therefore be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that al, &amp; ſmguler articles &amp; clauſes conteined in the ſaid diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as well touching the eſtablyſhment of Byſhopryckes, and cathedrall churches, as alſo the confirmation of marriages in degrees prohybi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the canons of the churche, the legittimation of chyldren, and the catification of proceſſe, and of ſentences in matters eccleſiaſtical, touchyng the iuualiditie of them for wante of iuriſdiction, and the in ſtitutions and diſtitituons. of. and in benefices and promotions eccle ſiaſticall, diſpenſations, and graces, gyuen by ſuch order, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like lawes of the realme then approued, and all other thinges before
<pb facs="tcp:25750:20"/>conteyned in the ſayd letters of diſpenſations, ſhall remayne &amp; be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and taken, to al intentes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructions in the lawes of this realme, lawefull, good, and effectuall to be alleged and pleaded in all courtes eccleſiaſticall and temporall, for good and ſufficiente matter, eyther for the playntyfe or defendaunt, without any allegation, or ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection, to be made againſt the validitie of them, by pretence of any ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall counſaile, canon, or decree, to the contrary made, or to be made in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And where as diuerſe and ſondrye late Monaſteryes, Pryoryes, Commaundryes, Nonneryes, Deaueries, Prebendes, Colleges, Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitales, Houſes of fryers, Chauntryes, and other religyous and eccle ſiaſticall houſes and places, and the manours, graunges, meſuages, landes, tenementes, rectoryes, tythes, pentions, portions, vycareges, churches, chappels, aduouſoues, nominations, patronages, annuities rentes, reuertions, ſeruyces, and other poſſeſſions, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to the ſayd late monaſteries, priories, nonneries. commaundryes, deaneryes, chauntryes, prebendes, houſes of fryers, colleges, Hoſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, and other religious and eccleſiaſtical houſes and places and to fondry Archebyſhopryckes, and Byſhopryckes within thys Realme, late appertaynyng and belongyng, came aſwell to the handes &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the ſayde kynge of famous memorye Henrye eyghte, father vnto your maieſtie, our ſaid ſoueraigne Ladye, by dyſſolution, gyfte graunt, ſurrendre, attaynder, or otherwyſe, as alſo to the handes and poſſeſſion of diuers and ſondrye other perſones, and bodyes polytyke and corporate, by ſondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the ordre of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme.</p>
            <p>And where alſo diuerſe manours, landes, tenementes, and heredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tamentes percell of the poſſeſſyons of Archbyſſhoprickes and byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rykes, and manye and ſondrye late deaneryes, colleges, chauntryes, rectories, Prebendes, Free Chappells, Gnyldes, and Fraternytyes, manours, houſes, Graunges, landes, Tenementes, rent<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, Seruices and other Eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, and heredytamentes, goodes, and cattels to the ſaid Archbyſſhopryckes, Byſſhopryckes, deaneries, colleges, chaunteryes, free chappels, rectories guyldes, and fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties late appertayning and belongynge or appointing, to and for the fyndyng of pryeſtes obyttes, lyghtes or other lyke purpoſe, came as wel to the handes &amp; poſſeſſion of the late noble kyng Edward the ſixr brother vnto your maieſtie ſoueraygne Lady, by vertue of an acte of parliament thereof made, or otherwiſe, as alſo to the handes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of diuerſe and ſondry other perſons and bodies polytyke and corporate by fondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the ordre of the lawes of this realine: a gret nomber of which ſaid late monaſteries, priories, nonneries, commaundres, deancryes, colleges, hoſpytales, prebendes, chaunteryes, free chappeles, guyldes,
<pb facs="tcp:25750:21"/>and fraternities, &amp; the mannours, graunges, meſuages, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes rentes, reuertions, ſeruices, tythes, pentions, portions vica reges, churches, chappels, aduouſons, nominations, patronages, an nuities, and hereditaments, goodes, and cattels, to the ſaid monaſte tyes, pryories, nonneries, commaundries, deaneries, colleges, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talles chauntries, fre chappels, guyldes, fraternities, and other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall houſes, Archbyſſhoprickes, and Byſhoprickes belonging as well for great ſommes of moneye, as for other good, and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſes, and conſiderations, haue beue conueyed and aſſured to di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe the ſubiectes, and bodyes politike of this realme, aſwell by the ſayd kyng Henry theight, the ſaid kynge Edwarde the ſixte, and by your highnes our ſoueraygne Lady, and ioyntly by both youre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, as alſo by dyuerſe the owners of the ſaid eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, which ſayd conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces by their ſondrye let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, and other wrytinges, more plainely do and maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Foraſmuch as the ſayd moſt reuerend father hath alſo by the ſaid diſpenſations, remoued and taken away al matter of empeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, trouble, and daunger, which by occaſion of any generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, canon, or degree eccleſiaſticall myghte touche and diſquite the poſſeſſions of ſuch goodes moueable, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſions and hereditamentes, as were of late belongynge to anye of the ſayde Archbyſſhopryckes, Byſhoprikes, monaſteryes, pryoryes, nonneries commaundries deaneryes, colleges, chauntryes, prebendes, rectori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, hoſpitales, houſes of fryers, or other religious and eccleſiaſticall houſes, and places of what nature name, kind, or qualitie ſoeuer thei be of. Yet for that the title of al landes, poſſeſſions, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in this your maieſties realme and dominions, is grounded in the lawes, ſtatutes and cuſtomes, of the ſame, and by your high iuryſoic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, aucthoritie royall, and crowne imperial, and in your courtes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be impleaded, ordered, tryed, and iudged, and none otherwiſe and vnderſtandyng, that the whole full and moſt gratious intentes mynd and determination of your moſt excellent maieſties be, that al and euery perſon and perſons, bodyes polytyke, and corporate, their heyres, ſucceſſours, and aſſignes, and euerye of them, ſhall haue, kepe, retayne and enioye al, and euerye their eſtates ryghtes, poſſeſſions, and intereſtes, that they and euerye of them nowe hath, or hereafter ſhall haue, of, and in al and euery the mannours, graunges, meſuages landes, tenementes, tythes, pencions, portions, aduouſons, nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, patronages, annuities, rentes, reuerſions, ſcruices, hundredes wapentakes, liberties, fraunchiſes, and other the poſſeſſyons, and he reditamentes of the ſayd monaſteries, abbeyes, proryes, nonneries commaundries, deaneries, colleges, prebendes, hoſpitales, houſes of fryers, chauntryes, rectoryes, vycareges, churches, chappelles, arch byſſhopryckes, and Byſſhoprikes, &amp; other religious or eccleſiaſticall
<pb facs="tcp:25750:21"/>houſes and places or of any of them within this realme, or the domy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the ſame by ſuche lawes and ſtatutes, as were in force before the fyrſt daye of this preſent Parlyament, and by other lawefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce to them thereof made.</p>
            <p>That it may be therfore enacted by thaucthoritie of this preſente parliament, that aſwell your maieſtie ſoueraigne Ladye, your heyres and ſucceſſours, as alſo all, and euery other perſon &amp; perſones bodies polytyke and corporate, their heires, ſucceſſours, &amp; aſſygnes nowe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, or that hereafter ſhall haue, holde or enioye anye of the ſeytes of the ſayd late monaſteries, and other the religious or eccleſiaſtycall houſes or places, and al the ſaid manours graunges, meſuages lands, tenementes, tithes, pentions, portions, glebelandes, aduouſonnes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, patronages, annuities, rentes, reuerſyons, ſeruyces hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes wapentakes liberties, fraunchiſes, profytes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, and other the poſſeſſions and hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the ſaide late monaſteries abbeyes, pryories, nonueries, commaundries, deaneries, colleges, prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, hoſpitals, houſes of friers, rectories, vicareges chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teris churches, chappels, archbiſhoprikes, biſſhoprikes and other religious &amp; eccleſiaſticall houſes and places, or of anye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what name, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or kynde ſoeuer they be, ſhall haue, holde, poſſede, retaine kepe &amp; enioye all and euery the ſayde ſcites, mannours, graunges, meſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, landes, tenemenees poſſeſſyons, profyttes, commodities, &amp; other hereditamentes, accordynge to ſuche intereſtes and eſtates, as they and euery of them nowe haue, or holde, or hereafter ſhal haue or holde of and in the ſame by the dewe ordre and courſe of the lawes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of thys realme, whiche nowe be, or were ſtandinge in force be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fyrſt day of this preſent Parliament, in maner and fourme, as they ſhoulde haue done, yf this acte had neuer bene had ne made Thys acte or any thinge herein contayned to the contrarye in anye wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Sauyng to you our ſayd ſoueraigne Lady, your heyres and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, and euerye of them, and to all and euerye other perion &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſubiectes of this realme, and bodyes politike and corporate, and to theyr heyres and ſucceſſours, and to the heires and ſucceſſours of al, and euery of them, other then ſuch, whoſe ryghte, tytle, or intereſte is bounden, or taken awaye, vndone, or extinct by anye acte of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment heretofore made, or otherwyſe al ſuch right, title, clayme, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, intereſtes, rentes, annuities, commodities, commons offyces, fees, leaſes liueries, lyuynges, pentions portions, dettes, dutyes, and other proffytes, which they, or any of them lawfully haue, or of ryghte ought to haue, or myghte to haue had, in of or to anye of the premyſſes or in, of or to any parte or percell thereof, in ſuch like maner &amp; fourme and condition, to all intentes, reſpectes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, as yf this acte had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:22"/>
            <p>And that it may be further enacted by aucthoritie aforeſaide, that al, and euery article, clauſe, ſentence, and prouiſo, conteined, or ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in any acte, or actes of Parliament, concerning, or touchyng the aſſuraunce, or conueiaunce of any the ſaid monaſteries priories, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neryes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundris, deaneries, prebendes, colleges, chauntryes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals, houſes, of fryers, rectories, vicarages, Churches, Chappeles Archbyſhoprickes, and Byſhoprickes, and other religyous and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical houſes, and places, or any of them, or in anyewiſe concerning any manuours, landes, tenementes, proffites, commodities heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or other the thynges, before ſpecified to the ſaid kinge Henrye theyght, or kynge Edwarde the ſyxte, or either of them, or anye other perſon or perſones, or body politike or corporate, and euerye of them and all, and euery writing, dede, and inſtrument, concernynge the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce of anye the ſame, ſhall ſtande, remayne, and be in as good force, effect, and ſtrength, and ſhalbe pleaded, and taken aduauntage of, to al intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, as the ſame ſhoulde, myght, or coulde haue bene by the lawes and ſtatutes of thys realme in caſe this preſent acte had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
            <p>And that al fe offamentes, fynes, ſurrenders, forfaytures, aſſuraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, conueyaunces, eſtates, and intereſtes, in any wyſe conueied, had or made to our ſayd late ſoucraygne lord kinge Henrye theyght or to our ſaid late ſoueraigne Lorde kinge Edwarde the ſixte, or eyther of them, or to any other perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, bodies polityke or corporate or to any of them by dede or dedes, act or actes of Parlyamente, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of any the ſcites, mannours, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſions profites, commodites, or hereditamentes of anye the ſayde Archebyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprikes, Byſhoprikes, late monaſteryes, priories, nonneries, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundries, deaneries, houſes, of fryars, colleges, chaunteryes, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, prebendes, fre chappels, or of any mannours, landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes reuertions, ſeruices, tithes, pentyons, portyons, annuities, or of any other hereditamentes, of by or from any eccleſiaſtycall or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon or perſons, or by, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſpiritual or eccleſiaſticall corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or body politike ſhalbe as good &amp; auailable in the lawe, to al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, as they were by the lawes &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this realme ſtanding in force before the firſt daye of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament. And that the ſame may, and ſhalbe pleaded, aleged &amp; taken aduauntage of, in ſuch ſorte, and to ſuch effect, as they ſhoulde could, or might haue ben by the lawes and ſtatutes of thys Realme, ſtanding in force before the ſaid fyrſt day of this preſent Parliament: And that all, and euery clauſe and article, of ſauinge conteined in all and euery the ſayd actes and ſtatutes, ſhall ſtand, remayne, and be in ſuch force, ſtrength, and effecte, as they were before the ſayde fyrſte day of this preſent parliament. Any thing conteined in this preſente acte to the concrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:22"/>
            <p>And that it maye be in like maner enacted by aucthoritie aforeſaid that whoſoeuer ſhal by any proceſſe, obteined out of any eccleſiaſticall court within this realme, or without, or by pretence of any ſpyrytuail iuriſdiction, or other wyſe, contrary to the lawes of this realme inqui et or moleſt any perſon or perſons, or bodye politike, for any of the ſaid manours, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, or thynges aboue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfyed, contrary to the wordes, ſentences, and meanynge of this acte ſhall incurre the daunger of the act of preminere, made in the xvi. yere of kyng Richarde the ſeconde, and ſhall ſuffer and ineurre the forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and paynes, conteined in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alway, that it ſhall and may be leafull to anye perſon or perſons, body politike and corporate, to ſue in any competente, eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall or ſpiritual court within this realme, for tythes, ryghtes, and dueties, that they or any of them ſhall pretende to haue, of or oute of any the ſayd manours, landes, tenementes, and other the premyſſes and to haue, full and perfect remedy for the fame, in ſuche maner and fourme, as they or any of them, mighte, or oughte to haue done, or had by the lawes and Statutes of this realme, before the makinge of this Acte, and as though this act had neuer ben had or made.</p>
            <p>And that it may be further prouyded and enacted, by thauetoritie aforeſayd, that albeit the title or ſtile of ſupremacye, or ſupreame hed of the churche of England and of Irelande, or eyther of them neuer was, ne coulde be iuſtly, or lawefully attributed or knowledged to any kynge, or Soueraygne gouernoure of thys realme, nor in anye wyſe could, or might, rightfully, iuſtly, or lawfully, by any king or ſoueraign gouernour of this realm, be claimed chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, or vſed. Yet foraſmuch as the ſayde tytle and ſtyle, ſythens the thyrde daye of Nouember, in the .xxvi. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde kynge Henrye the eyghte, hath bene vſed, and is mentioned and conteyned in dyuers and ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye wrytes, letters patentes, recordes, exemplyfycatyons, coute rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, charters, dedes, inſtrumentes, euydences, bokes and wrytynges. It ſhalbe lawefull, aſwell to, and for youre Maieſtyes and your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne ladies heyres and Succeſſoures, as to, and for euerye other perſon, and perſones, and bodies politike and corporate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aſ altime and times here after, to haue, retayne, and kepe the ſayd wrytes, letters pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentes, recordes, exemplifications, courte rolles Charters, dedes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes, euidences, bokes, and vorytynges, and them to ſhewe, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibite, vſe, alledge, and pleade, in all tymes and places requpſyte, or nedeful, without any daunger penaltye, loſſe, for feyture, trouble, vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, or impeachment for the ſame, anye thynge in thys acte, or in any other acte or actes, to the contrary thereof in anye wyſe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
            <p>And wher your highnes Soueraygne Lady, ſynce your comming to the crowne of this realme, of a good and Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſcience, omyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:25750:23"/>to write the ſaide Style of Supremacye, ſpecyfyed in one Acte made in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter by prorogation in the xxxv. yeare of the raygne of your late father kynge Henrye theyghte, aſwell in gyftes, grauntes, letters patentes, as in commyſſyons, and other wrytynges, and alſo other haue in theyr wrytynges done the ſame aſwell in your tyme as before. And foraſmuche as notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng any lawe made concernynge the ſayde Style of Supremacye, it was in the free choyſe, libertye, and pleaſure of the kynge of thys realme, and of your hyghnes, whether ye woulde expreſſe the ſame in the ſayd Style or not.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore declared and enacted by aucthoritie of this preſente parlyament, that all grauntes, letters, patentes, commiſſions indyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, recordes, and wrytinges, made in youre oure Soueraygne Ladies name, or in the names of yours Soueraygne Lorde and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or any other, wherein the ſaid Style of Supremacye is omytted is, and ſhalbe, to all intentes and purpoſes, as good and effectuall, as yf the ſame had bene therein expreſſed, &amp; may be deteined, kepte, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and alleged, without any daunger, paine, penaltie, or forfayture to enſue to any perſon or perſones, or body politike, for or concerninge the omiſſion of the ſame Style, or any parte thereof, in any ſuch wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, &amp; that no perſon ne perſons, ſhalbe impeached, moleſted, or da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p nyfyed, for or by reaſon of any ſuch omyſſyon.</p>
            <p>And where in an acte of parliament made ſince the ſayde .xx. yeare of kynge Henrye theyghte, all Bulles, diſpenſations, and wrytynges which were before that tyme optained fyom the Sea of Rome, ſhould be voyde, avolyſhed, and extinguiſhed, with a clauſe, neuertheles that the matter of them, by vertue of letters patentes from the kyng then beinge ſhoulde, and mighte be alleged, pleeded, and allowed, as yf the ſame had not bene ſoo aboliſbed or extinguyſhed. Foraſmuche as the ſayd acte is here before amongeſt other repealed and made voyde.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore euacted by aucthoritie of this preſent parlyamente that all Bulles, diſpenſations, and pryuyleges, obteyned before thee ſayde .xx. yeare, or at any tyme ſythence, or whyche ſhall hereafter be optemed of the Sea of Rome, not conteininge matter contrarye or pretudicial to the aucthoritie, dygnytye, or prehemynence Royall, or imperyall of the realme, or to the lawes of this realme, nowe beyng in force, and not in this parliament repealed, maye be put in executyon, vſed and alleged in anye courte within thys Realme, or ells where whether the ſame remayne yet hole, or can appeare to haue bene can celled, in this vayleable and effectuall maner, to all intentes, &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as yf the ſayd Acte had neuer bene had or made. Anye obiectyon by pretence of extinguyſhment, or cancellyng of the ſayd Bulles, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, or priuileges, or of any other matter or cauſe, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the lawes of thys realme, whatſoeuer in anye wyſe notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:23"/>
            <p>And wher as by diſſolution of monaſteries, and other religious houſes, certayne paryſhe churches and chappeles which wer before exempte, from the iuriſdiction of the Archbyſhope and byſhop of the dioceſſe, and by ſpeciall exemption and priuelege from Rome, were vnder the gouernement and order of the Abbotes, and Prioures of thoſe religious houſes, whych ſayde churches by colour of the ſayd exemptions, be nowe of ſpeciall graunt from Kyng Henry, &amp; kynge Edwarde, vnder the rule and gouernement, and iuriſdiction of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and laye men, who can no more enioye, that ſuprmacye, ouer thoſe particuler churches, then the king might ouer the hole realme</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted, that all Archbyſhoppes, &amp; byſhopes in their dioces, and all other ſpirituall perſon and perſones, hauynge iuriſdiction, and their miniſteres and officers, and no laye perſon, or perſones in euery Churche and place, within the precincte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame beyng rempte, or not exempte, maye freely, and without impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t execute their ſpirituall iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al pointes &amp; articles, as though no ſuch exemption or graunt had neuer bene made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaye, and be it enacted, that this act extend not to take awaye, or oiminyſhe the preuileges, of the vniuerſitie of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge and Oxforde, ne the priuileges, or prerogatiues graunted heretofore to the churches of Weſtminſter, and Wyndeſore, ne the Tower of London, ne preiudiciall, to ſuche temporall Lordes and poſſeſſioners in this realme, as by auncient cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e haue emoyed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of Teſtamentes, of their tenauntes or other.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch, as after this reconſiliation, and vnitie of this no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble realme, to the body of Chriſtes church, it is to be truſted, that by the aboundaunce of goddes marcy, and grace, deuotion ſhal encreſe and growe in the hartes of many the Subieces of this realme, with deſire to gyue &amp; beſtow their worldly poſſeſſions, for the reſuſcita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of almoſe, prayer, &amp; example of good life in this realme, to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſuch godly motions and purpoſes ſhould be aduaunced.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by aucthoritye of this preſent parlyame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it ſhalbe lawefull to ſuche as ſhalbe ſeſſed of any mauours, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds tene mentes, perſonages tithes, pencions, portions, or other heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, whatſoeuer in fee ſymple, in poſeſſion, reuertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in their owne ryghtes, not veyng coppy holde, may therof make feoffamentes, grauntes, or any other aſſuraunces, or by his laſt wyll and Teſtament, in wryting, may be queath and geue in fe ſymple, al and euery the ſayd manours, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenementes perſonages, tithes pentions, portions, or other hereditamentes, to any ſpyrituall body polytike, or corporate in this realme or dominions of the ſame, nowe erected or founded, or hereafter to be erected or founded: withoute any lycence of mortmayne there in to be optayned: or any wrytte of
<pb facs="tcp:25750:24"/>
               <hi>ad quod dampnum</hi> to be ſued out for the ſame, the actes <hi>de terri ad manion mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam non ponendis</hi> or any other acte or ſtatute, heretofore had or made in in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Sauyng to the Lordes of the fee, all rentes, ſeruices dew, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng out of any of the ſayde land or renements, or hereditaments, ſo to be amortized, as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this clauſe of this acte, for geuing the liber tye of, or for the amortezyng of landes or tenementes, ſhall cotynue for, and duryng the ſpace of .xx. yeares nexte, and immediatelye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, and no lenger.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as we your maieſties humble and obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent Parlyament aſſembled, nether by the makyng, or deliuering of either the ſupplycations aforeſayde, nor by any clauſe, artycle or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence thereof, or of any other clauſe article or ſentence of this or any other Statute, or any of the preambles of the ſame, made, or agreed vpon in this ſeſſion of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by any maner of inter pretation, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruction, implication or other wyſe intende to derogate empaire, or diminiſh any of the prerogatiues, liberties, fraunchiſies preheminences, or iuriſdictyons of your Croune Imperyall of thys realme, and other the dominions to the ſame belonging, we do moſt humbly beſech your maieſtyes, that it maye be declared, and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and be it enacted and declared by aucthoritie of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that neither the makyng, exhibityng, or inſertynge in thys preſent ſtatute, or in the preambles of the ſame, of the ſupplicatyons or promys aforeſayd, or either of them; nor any other thyng or thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wordes, ſentences, clauſes, or articles, in the preambles or body of the artes, aforeſayde, ſhalbe conſtrued vnderſtanded or expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to derogat, diminiſhe or take away any the liberties, priuileges, pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogatiues, preheminences, authorities, or iuriſdictyons or any parte or pertel therof, which were in your imperial croune of this realme or dyd belong to your ſayde imperial croune the twenty yere, of the reigne of yours the Quenes maieſties moſte noble father, or anye other your moſt noble progenitours, before the ſayd twentye yere, &amp; the popes holynes, and Sea Apoſtolyke, to be reſtored, and to haue and enioye ſuch aucthoritie, prehemynence, and inriſdictyon as hys holines, vſed, and exerciſed, or myght lawfully haue vſed and excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by aucthoritie of hys ſupremacie, the ſayd twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie yeare of the regine of the kinge your father, within this youre realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nde, &amp; other your Dominions, without diminution, or enlargeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſame and none other. And the Ecleſiaſticall iuriſdiction of the Archebiſhoppes, Biſhoppes, and ordinaties, to be in the ſame ſtate, for proceſſe of ſuites, puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of crimes, and execution of cenſures of the churche, wyth knowledge of cauſes belongyng to the ſame, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25750:24"/>as large in theſe poyntes, as the ſayde iuriſdiction was the ſaide .xx. eyare.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauethoritie aforeſayd, that in and vpon euery ſuch gyftes and deuyſes, to be made to ſuche ſpirituall corporations, or perſones as is aforeſaid, the donor feoffer, or diuiſor thereof may reſerue to him, and to his heires for euer, a tenure in franke almaine, or a tenure by diuine ſeruice: and to haue al reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and actions, for and vpon the ſaid giftes, or deuyſes, and tenures in lyke maner &amp; ſorme, as was vſed before the eſtatute of Weſtminſter thyrd (commonly called) <hi>Quia emptores terrarum.</hi> The ſayde eſtatute or any other lawe or cuſtome nowe beyng to the contrarye in anye wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted, that all and euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; perſones, and bodies politike and corporate which nowe haue or here after ſhall haue any eſtate of enheritaunce, frehold, terme, or intreſt, of in, or to any portion, pention, tithes, glebelandes, or other eccleſyaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or ſpirituall profytte; which by thys acte, and letters of diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rehearſed in the ſame, be permitted &amp; ſuffered to remayne &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in laye mens poſſeſſions, ſhall and maye haue lyke remedye for the recouerye of the ſame, and euery parte thereof as they and euery of them myght haue had before the fyrſte daye of thys preſent Parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, Anye thyng in this acte conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yned to the contrary in anywiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for the puniſhment of traiterous wordes agaynſt the Quenes Maieſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .ix. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as nowe of late diuerſe noughty ſedicyous malicious, &amp; heretical perſons, not hauyng the fere of god before their eies, but in a deuiliſhe ſort, contrarye to the duetie of their allegiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, haue congregated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues together in conuenticles, in dyuerſe and ſondry prophane places within this citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don eſteming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to be in the true faith, wher in dede they are in errous &amp; here ſies, &amp; oute of the true trade of Chryſtes catholyke religyon, &amp; in the ſame places at ſeuerall tymes, vſing theyr phantaſticall and ſcyſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſeruyces, lately taken awaye, and abolyſhed by aucthoritie of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament, haue of theyr moſt malicious &amp; cankerde ſtomakes, prayed agaynſt the Quenes maieſtie, that God would turne her herte from Idoltrye to the true faythe, or ells to ſhorten her dayes, or take her quickely out of the waye, whiche prayer was neuer harde nor rede to haue bene vſed by anye good Chryſtyan manne, agaynſte anye
<pb facs="tcp:25750:25"/>Prynce though he were a pagan, and infidele, and much leſſe againſt any chriſtian Prince, and eſpecially ſo vertuous a Princes, as our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne Lady that nowe is knowen to be, whoſe faythe is and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath bene moſt true and catholyque, and conſonaunt and agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with Chriſtes catholique Churche, throughout the world dyſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>For reformation wherof, be it enacted by thauctoritie of thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament, that euery ſuch perſon and perſones, which ſince the begynnyng of this preſent parliament, haue by expreſſe wordes and ſayinges, prayed, required, or deſired, as is aforeſayde, or hereafter ſhal pray, by expreſſe wordes or ſayinges, that God ſhoulde ſhortenne her dayes, or take her out of the way (whoſe lyfe almighty God longe preſerue) or any ſuche lyke malicious prayer, amountinge to the ſame effect, theyr procurers and abbettours therein, ſhalbe taken, reputed and iudged traytours, and euery ſuch prayinge, requiringe, or deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng ſhalbe indged, taken, and reputed hygh treaſon, and the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours therin, their procurers and abbettours, beyng thereof lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuycte, accordyng to the lawes of thys Realme, ſhall haue, ſuffer and forfeyte, as in caſes of hygh treaſon.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouyded alway and be it enacted, that yf any perſon or perſones ſhall be indycted for any the offences aforeſayd, done and perpetrated duryng this ſeſſion of this preſent parlyament, and vpon hys or their arraygnment, ſhall ſhewe him or them ſelues penytente for there of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and ſubmitte him or them ſelues to the kyng and Quenes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and humbly deſyre the ſame, before ſuch Iuſtices or commiſſioners before whom he or they ſhalbe arraygued, that then no iudgement or conuiction or attayndour of treaſon, ſhalbe geuen agaynſte any ſuche perſon or perſones, ſo beyng penytent, and ſubmyttynge them ſelues, as is aforeſayd. And in euery ſuch caſe, the Iuſtices or commiſſioners before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch perſon or perſons ſhalbe arraigned, ſhal haue auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by vertue of this acte, to preſcribe, adiudge, and appoynte, ſuche corporall puniſhment, other then death, to ſuch offender and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders as to them by their diſcretion ſhall ſeme conuenyente, and vpon that penaunce preſcribed and done, to be diſcharged of the ſayde treaſon, compriſed in that inditement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte whereby certayne offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kynges and Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties iſſue.</head>
            <head type="sub">☞ The .x. Chapter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:25"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuch as the greate mercy &amp; clemency hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared by the Queenes hyghnes, in releaſing the penal lawes, made by her progenitours, hath gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to many cankarde &amp; trayterous harts to ymagyne, practyſe, &amp; attempte things ſtirryng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to diſobedience, &amp; rebellyon agaynſt her hyghnes common polecy, and duetye of ſubiectes, requyre that ſome lawe be eftſons eſtablyſhed to reſtrayne the malyce of ſuch wycked and euyll doors, wherby they may be prehibited to blowe abroade ſuch ſhame full ſlaunders and lyes, as they daylye inuente and yinagine of her highnes and the kynges maieſtie her mooſt lawefull huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which when they be hard can not be but odible, and deteſted of all good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſyderyng they touche their maieſtyes vpon whome dependeth the whole vnitie and vniuerſall wealth of this realine.</p>
            <p>In conſideratydn wherof be it ordeined and enacted by the king and the quenes maieſties, with thaſſent of the lordes ſpyrituall and temporall, and of the commons in thys preſent parſyament aſſebled and by the auctorytye of the ſame, that yf any perſo or perſons after the firſt daye of February next to com duryng the maryage betwen the king &amp; the quenes maieſties, do compaſſe or imagine to depriue the kynges maieſtie, that nowe is, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hauyng &amp; inioyning ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together with the quenes highnes the ſtile, honour, and kynglye name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realmes and dominions vnto our ſayd ſoueraygne Lady the quenes hyghnes apertaining, or to deſtroie the kyng that nowe is, duryng the ſayd matrimonye, or to deſtroye the quenes maieſtie that nowe is, or the heires of her bodye begotten, beynge kynges or Queenes of thys Realme, or to leuye warre wythyn thys Realme of England, or wythin any of the marches of the ſame, agaynſte the kynges maieſtie, that nowe is, duryng the ſayd maryage or agaynſt the quenes maieſtie that nowe is or any of her ſayde heyres, beyng kinges or quenes of this Realme, or to depoſe the quenes maieſtie that nowe is, or the heires of her body begotten, beynge kynges or queenes of thys realme, from the Imperyall croune of the realmes and dominions aboue ſayd. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaine compaſſes, or imaginations or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, ſhall, or do vtter by open preaching, expreſſe wordes, or ſayinges or if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones after the ſayd fyrſt day of February by preching expreſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or ſayinges, ſhal maliciouſly, aduifedly, and directlye, ſaye pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, declare, maintaine or hold opinion, that the kynges maieſtye, that now is during the ſaid matrimony, ought not to haue or enioy ioyntlye together with the queenes maieſtie, the ſtile, honoure, and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, being ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kyng or the quenes maieſties that nowe are durynge the ſayd matrimony betweue them, ought to haue or enioye the ſtile, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure,
<pb facs="tcp:25750:26"/>and kyngelye name of this realme, or that the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that nowe is, during her life, is not, or of right oughte not to be quene of this realme, or after her death, that the heyres of her hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body beyng kinges or quenes of this realme of righte oughte not to be kynges or quenes of this realme, or to haue and enioye the ſame or that anye perſon or perſonnes, other then the quenes maieſtie, that nowe is during her life, ought to be Quene of this realme, or after her death other then the heyres of her body beinge kinges or queenes of this realme, as longe as any of her ſayde heyres of her body begotten ſhalbe in lyfe, of ryght oughte to haue and enioy the imperiall crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuche offendoour, beyng therof duly connicted, or attainted by the lawes of this realme, their abbettours procurers, and counſailoures, and all, and euerye theyr comforters, knowynge the ſayde offences, or anye of theym to bee done, and being thereof conuicted or attaynted, as is aboueſayde, for his or theyr ſuche offence, ſhall forfeyte and loſe to the queenes hyghnes, her heyres and ſucceſſours, all his and theyr goodes, and cattels, and the whole iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and proffytes of his and theyr landes, tenementes, and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, ſor terme of the lyfe of euerye ſuche offendoure or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and alſo ſhall haue, and ſuffer, duringe his and theyr liues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall impriſonment.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that all and euery eccleſiaſticall perſon beinge conuicted or attaynted in fourme aforeſaid, for euery ſurhe his offence, ſhalbe depriued by the ordinary from his promotion ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall, in ſuche lyke maner and fourme, that it ſhalbe laweful for euery patron, founder or geuer thereof, to preſent, after ſuche depriuation hadde, ſome one other to the ſame, as thoughe the ſayde offendoure or offendoures, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſed. And yf any perſon or perſons beyng hereafter conuicted or at taynted of any of the ſayd offences, in fonrme aforeſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſhal after his or theyr conuiction, or attainder, eſtſones committe or perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate any of the ſayde offences, in forme aforeſayde. That then euerye ſuche ſeconde offence or offences ſhalbe demed, and adiudged hyghe treaſon, and the offendoure or offendoures therein, theyr abbettoures procurers, and councelloures, and all and euery theyr aydours &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters, knowing the ſayd offences, or anye of them to be done, beyng thereof conuicted or attainted, accordyng to the lawes and Statutes of this realme, ſhalbe iudged and demed hyghe traytoures, and ſhall ſuffer paynes of deathe, and loſe and forfeyte all theyr goodes, and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels landes, and tenementes, to the queenes maieſtie, her heyres and ſucceſſours, as in caſes of high treaſon, by the lawes of this realme at this day, of ryght ought to be loſt and forfeyted.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the ſaid aucthoritie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yf any perſon or perſones at any time after the ſaid firſt day of February next to come
<pb facs="tcp:25750:26"/>during the ſayd marriage, compaſſe, or ymagine the death of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, that nowe is, and the ſame maliciouſely, aduiſedly and di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rectly ſhall vtter and attempte by any writing, pryntynge, ouert dede or acte, or yf any perſon or perſons at any tyme after the ſaid fyrſt day of February next comming, ſhall maliciouſly, aduiſedlye, and dyrectlye by wryting, prynting, ouert dede, or acte, affirme that the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that nowe is, duryng the ſaid matrimony, oughte not to haue or enioye ioyntly togethers with the Quenes hyghnes, the ſtyle, honour and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſon or perſons, beyng neither the kynge, or the Quenes maieſtie, that nowe is, durynge the ſayde matrimony betwene them ought to haue and enioy the ſtile ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and kinglye name of this realme. Or yf any perſon or perſonnes after the ſayde day by any writing, prynting, ouert dede, or acte, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſely, aduiſedly, and directly, do affirme that the Quenes maieſtie that nowe is, duryng her lyfe is not, or oughte not to be quene of this realme, or after her death, that the heyres of her hyghnes body beyng kynges or Quenes of this realme, of ryght ought not to haue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the imperiall Crowne of this Realme, or that anye perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones other then the Quenes maieſtie that nowe is, durynge her lyfe or after her death, other then the heyres of her body begotten, beynge kynges or quenes of this realme, as longe as anye of her ſayde heyres of her body ſhalbe in lyfe, of ryghte oughte to haue and enioye the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryall crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuch offence and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhalbe adiudged high treaſon, &amp; the offender &amp; offenders therein, theyr abbettours, procurers, and councellers, and all and euery theyr aydours, and comforters, knowinge the ſayd offences, or any of them to be done, beynge thereof conuicted, or attaynted by the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, ſhal be demed and adiudged hygh traytoures, and ſhall ſuffer paynes of death, and looſe and forfeyte al theyr goodes and cattels, landes, and tenementes to the Quenes maieſtie, her hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſucceſſours as in caſes of high treaſon, as is aboueſayde.</p>
            <p>And albeit we the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, haue fyrme hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the goodnes of Almyghty God, that lyke as he hath hether to mir aculouſiye preſerued the Quenes maieſty from many greate &amp; imminent periles &amp; daungers, euen ſo he wyll of his infinite goodnes gyue her highnes ſtrength, the rather by oure continuall prayers to paſſe well the daunger of deliueraunce of chylde wherwith it hathe pleaſed hym (to all oure greate comfortes) to bleſſe her. Yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as all thinges of thys worlde be vncertayne, and hauynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the dolorous experience of the inconſtaut gouernement duringe the tyme of the reygne of the late kynge Edwarde the ſyxte, do playnelye ſe the manifolde inconuenienees, greate daungers, and perylles, that maye enſue to this hole realme, yf foreſyghte be not vſed
<pb facs="tcp:25750:27"/>to preuent euyll chaunces, yf they ſhould happen. For the eſchewing whereof, we the Lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled for &amp; in conſideration of a moſt ſpecial truſt and confidence, that we haue &amp; repoſe in the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, for and concernyng the good and politike gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ordre, and adminiſtration of this realme in the tyme of the yonge yeres of the iſſue or iſſues of her maieſties body to be borne, if it ſhould pleaſe God to call the quenes hyghnes out of thys preſent lyfe duryng the tender yeares of ſuch iſſue or iſſues (whych God forbyde) according to ſuch ordre and maner as hereafter in this preſent acte, hys hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt gratious pleaſure is ſhould be declared and ſet fourth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue made our moſt humble ſuite by thaſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quenes highnes that his maieſtie would vouchſafe to accepte and take vpon him the rule ordre, educatyon, and gouernement of the ſayde iſſue or iſſues to be borne, as is aforeſayd, vpon which our ſuit being of his ſaid maieſtie moſt graciouſly accepted. It hath pleaſed his highnes not onely to declare, that like as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt part his maieſtie verely truſteth that almighty God, who hath hetherto preſerued the quenes maieſtie to giue this realme ſo good an hope of certayne ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the blud roial of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame realme, wil aſſiſt her highnes with his graces &amp; bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſee the frute of her bodye wel broughte forth liue, and able to gouerne, whereof nether all thys realme ne al the world beſydes ſhold or coulde receaue more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, then hys maieſtie ſhuld &amp; wold. Yet yf ſuch chaunce ſhuld happen, his maieſtie at our humble deſires is pleaſed and contented, not alonely to except and take vp o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure and charg of the education, rule, ordre, and gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch iſſues, as of this moſt happy mariage ſhalbe borne betwene the que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes highnes and him, but alſo during the time of ſuch gouernement wold by alwayes and meanes ſtudy, trauayle and employe himſelfe to aduaunce the weale, bothe publique and priuat of thys realme, &amp; dominions there vnto belongyng, accordyng to the ſaid truſt in his maieſtye repoſed, with no leſſe good wyll and affectyon, then ythys hyghnes had byne naturally borne amongeſt vs.</p>
            <p>In conſyderatyon wherof be it enacted by the kyng &amp; the quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt excellent maieſtyes, by thaſſent of the Lordes ſpirytuall &amp; temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that yf it ſhal ſo pleaſe God, to call the quenes maieſtie out of this preſent lyfe, which god forbydde, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the iſſue of her body, inheritable to the Crowne of this realm if it be male ſhal accompliſhe the age of .xviii. yeres, or if it be female, before it ſhalbe of the age of .xv. yeares, and not maryed after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of conſent, and before the ſayd age of .xv. yeares. That then &amp; unme diatly after, and from the deceaſſe of our ſayd Soueraygne Lady y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> quene, the kinges maieſtie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nowe is, ſhall haue the rule, order, edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:25750:27"/>and gouernment of the perſon of ſuche iſſue, or iſſues, and the rule, ordre &amp; gouernement (vnder ſuch iſſue, or iſſues) of this realme, and the dominions to the ſame belongynge, vntyll the ſame iſſue or iſſues, inheritable to the imperyall Crowne of thys Realme, yf it bee male, ſhall accomplyſhe the fall age of eightene yeares and yf it be fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, vntill ſuch iſſue female, ſhalbe accomplyſhe the age of fyuetene yeares, and be maried after the age of conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and before the ſaid age offyuetene yeares, if the ſaid iſſue or iſſues, and oure ſaid ſoueraigne Lord the king, ſhal ſo long liue together, and that duringe, and by all the tyme of ſuch gouernement, all, and euery the pactes, couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, articles, and agrementes, mentioned and comyryſed in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, and acte of Parliament, and euery of them made, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for and concernyng the honourable mariage, had and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, betwene the Kyng and Quenes Maieſties, whych on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of his Maieſtie, bene to be obſerued, perfourmed &amp; kepte, ſhall after the deceaſſe of the Quenes Maieſtie, durynge the tyme of the ſayd gouernement, remaine, continue, and be in as good, and ful force ſtrength, and effecte, to all intentes, and purpoſes, as they were at any tyme, duryng the ſayde Maryage, or nowe bene, as yf they were newly by apte wordes, termes, and ſentences, inſerted and reherſed in this preſent Act, and newely made and enacted, to ſtand, remaine continue, and to be obſerued, and kept, durynge the tyme of the ſayde gouernmente, and ſhalbe by his Maieſtie, duringe the ſaide tyme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolablye obſerued perfourmed, mainteined, and vpholden, in ſuche ſorte, and in as full large, and ample maner, to all reſpectes, as they ſhould and ought to be, duryng the tyme of the ſayd maryage, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and his highnes, and the Quenes moſt excellent Maieſtye, are pleaſed and contented, that it be enacted by thys preſent Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that nothyng ſhalbe done permitted, or aſſented vnto by hys Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that yf any perſon or perſones, duryng the tyme that our ſayd ſoueraigne lorde the kynge that nowe is, ſhal, and ought to haue the ordre, rule, educa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and gouernement of ſuch iſſue or iſſues, being kynge or Quene of this realme, according to theordre and prouiſion aforeſaid maly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, by wrytynge, prynting, ouert dede or acte dooe compaſſe, attempt, and go aboute to deſtroye the perſonne of our ſaid ſoueraynge lord, or do depryue, or remoue his ſayde hygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes from the order, rule, education, and gouernement of the ſame iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue or iſſues, beyng kynge or Quene of this realme, contrarye to the tenoure, entente, and true meaning of this preſent act, that then eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſuch perſon or perſones ſo offendyng, their procurers and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, beyng there of lawfully conuicte or attaynted by the lawes of this realme, ſhalbe demed and adiudged high Traitours: And that
<pb facs="tcp:25750:28"/>all and euerye ſuche offence and offences, ſhalbe demed and adiudged hygh treaſon. And the offendour and offendours therein, theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers, counſaylours, and abbettours, ſhall incurre the daungers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytures, and penalties of hygh treaſon.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaid that al tryals hereafter to be had, awarded, or made, for any treaſon, ſhalbe had, and vſed onely, accordyng to the due order &amp; courſe of the common lawes of this realme, and not otherwyſe. Sauyng to euery perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, bodyes polytyke and corporate, their heires, and ſucceſſoures other then the offendours, and their heires and ſuche perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as clayme to any of theyr vſes, all ſuch ryghtes, tytles, intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, poſſeſſions, leaſſes, rentes, reuertions, offyces, and other profytes, whych they or any of them ſhall haue at the daye of the committynge ſuch treaſones, or at any tyme afore, in as large and ample maner, as if this acte had neuer bene had or made.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it declared and enacted by thaucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforeſayd, that conceylement, or kepyng ſecrete of anye hygh trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be demed and taken onely, miſpriſyon of treaſon &amp; the offenders therein to forfeyt, and ſuffer, as in caſes of miſpriſion of treaſon hath heretofore bene vſed. Anye thynge aboue mentioned, to the contrarye notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alſo, that if it ſhall fortune hereafter any of the peares of this realme, to be indicted of any of the offences made treaſon or myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſyon of treaſon by thys acte, that then the ſame peares, or peare, ſoo beynge indycted, ſhalbe put to aunſwere vnto euerye ſuche endyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before the hygh ſtewarde of Englande for the tyme beyng and to haue his and their tryall by hys and their peares, and to receaue &amp; haue ſuch lyke iudgement vpon the ſame tryall of hys or their peares, or makyng open confeſſion of the ſame offence, or offences as is vſed in other caſes of hygh treaſon.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons ſhall in any wyſe be impeached for any of the offences aboueſayd, commytted onely by open preachynge or wordes, onleſſe the offender of offenders be therefore indited within ſixe moneths, next after the ſame open preaching or wordes. Anye thing conteined in this acte to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd that vpon the arraygment of any perſon, whiche hereafter ſhall for tune to be arraygned for any treaſon, mentioned in this acte, all and euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſones, or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leaſt, as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after wryte, declare, confeſſe, or depoſe any thing or thynges agaynſt the perſon to be arraygned, ſhall, yf they be then liuing &amp; within the realme be brought forth in perſon before the partye arraygned, yf he requyre the ſame, and obiecte, and ſaye openly in his herynge what
<pb facs="tcp:25750:28"/>they or any of them can agaynſt him, for or concerning any the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones, conteined in the indictment, wher vpon the partye ſhalbe ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raygned, onleſſe the partye arraygned for any ſuch treaſon, ſhal wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly confeſſe the ſame at the time of his or their arraignement.</p>
            <p>Prouided neuer theleſſe, &amp; be it enacted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thauchoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde that in al caſes of hyght treaſon, concernynge coyne curraunt within this realme, or for counterfeytyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king or Quenes ſygnet pryuie ſeale, great ſeale, or ſygne manuel, ſuch maner of tryal &amp; none other be obſerued and kept as heretofore hath bene vſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes of this realme. Any lawe ſtatute, or any other thynge or thynges to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Pronyded alwayes, that the counſellours, procurers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forters, and abbettonrs for his or their firſt offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re ſhal ſuffer like puniſhment penaltie, and forfeyture, as is conteyned in this acte againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal offendours, for their firſt offence and none other, And that the councellours, procurers comforters, &amp; abbettoures, for his or thier ſecond offence ſhall ſuſteyne lyke punyſhment, penaltie, &amp; forfeytur as is conteyned in this act agaynſt the principal offendour or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doures for their ſecond offence, and none other.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>¶ And acte for the puniſhment of brynging in of couterfeyte coyne of forrayne realmes, beynge curraunte wythin this realme.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .xi. Chapiter,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here diuerſe and ſondrye coynes of golde and ſiluer of other realmes, not beynge of the propre coyne of thys realme of Englande, and yet by the ſufferaunce and conſent of the kyng and quene our Soueraygne Lord and Lady, be curraunt in paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t within this realme, many yl diſpoſed perſons for thir owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte lucre &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, haue nowe of late brought into this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, from the parties of beyonde the ſea, greate quantitie of forged and counter fayte mony, lyke to the ſaid coine of other forreyne real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and haue vttered the ſame here by marchaundiſing, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe to diuerſe of the ſubiectes of this realme, to their greeat deceit hurt &amp; damage becauſe the ſayde yl dyſpoſed perſones hane percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vnderſtanded, that there was not, nor yet is any ſufficiente lawe or ſtatute made or prouyded for the condygne punyſhment of the offendours in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore be it enacted and eſtablyſhed by the auc thorytye of this preſent Parliament, that if any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye daye of Ianuary nexte commynge, ſhal bryng from the partyes
<pb facs="tcp:25750:29"/>of beyond the ſea into this realme, or into any the dominions of the ſame any ſuch falſe and counterfeyte coyne or money, beyng cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t within thys realme as is aforeſayd, knowyng the ſame coine or money to be falſe and counterfeite, to thintent to vtter, or make pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the ſame within this realme or any the dominions of the ſame, by marchaundiſyng, or otherwyſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all and euery ſuch perſon or perſones ſo offen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng, as is aforeſayd, their counſailours, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, aydours, and abbettours in that behalfe ſhalbe demed &amp; iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be offendours in high treaſon, and ſhall ſuffer after lawefull conuiction or attaynder thereof, ſuch paines of death, loſſe and forfai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, of landes, goodes, &amp; cattelles, as other offendoures ſhal do, in caſes of high treaſon.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that all, &amp; euery perſon and perſons, that ſhall at any tyme after the ſayde .xx. day of Ianuary, be accuſed or impeched of any of the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, contei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and prouided for in this eſtatute, or of any other offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concernyng the impayrynge counterfeytyng, or forgyng of any coyne curraunte within this realme, ſhall and maye be endicted, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyned, tryed, conuicted, or atteynted by ſuche like euidence, and in ſuch maner and fourme as hath ben vſed &amp; accuſtomed within this realme, at any tyme before the tyrſte yeare of the raygne of our late ſone raygne lord king Edward the ſixt. Any ſtatute, cuſtome lawe, or vſage to the contrarye there of in any wyſe notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for the impounding of diſters.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .xii. Chapyter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the auoydyng of greuous vexations, exactions, troubles, and diſorder in taking of deſtreſſes and im poundynge of cartel, be it enacted by aucthorytye of this preſent Parlyment, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; after the firſt dai of Apryl next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, no diſtreſſe of catel ſhalbe dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, rape, wapentake, or lath, where ſuch diſtreſſes is, or ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except it be to a pound, ouert with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd ſhire, not aboue thre myles diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, from the place where the ſayd diſtreſſe is taken, &amp; that no cattell, or other goodes diſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or taken by way of diſtreſſe, for any maner of cauſe: at one tyme ſhalbe impou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in ſeueral places, whereby the owner or owners of ſuch dyſtreſſe ſhalbe conſtrayned to ſue ſeuerall repleuis for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the ſayde diſtreſſe, ſo taken at one time, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payne euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon offendyng contrary to this act ſhal forefeyt to the party greued for euery ſuch offence a hundred ſhillinges and treble damages.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by aucthoritie aforeſayd, that after
<pb facs="tcp:25750:29"/>the ſaid fiſt day of Apryll, no perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons ſhall take for kepynge inpounde, impounding, or pondage of any maner of diſtreſſe, aboue the ſomme of .iiii. pence for any one whole diſtreſſe, that ſhalbe ſo im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded, and where leſſe hath bene vſed, ther to take leſſe, vpon the payne of fyue pound to be payd to the party greued, ouer &amp; beſydes ſuch mony as he ſhal take aboue the ſome of foure pence. Any vſage or preſcription to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>And for the more ſpedier deliuery of cattell, taken by waye of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, it is further enacted by the ſayd aucthoritie, that euery Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, of ſhires, being no cities nor townes made ſhyres, ſhall at his firſt countie day, or within two monethes next after he hath recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his patente of his office of ſhiriſwike, ſhall depute, appoint &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clayme in the ſhyre towne within his baylyweke, foure deputies at the leaſt, dwellyng not aboue twelue myles one diſtaunt from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which ſayd deputies ſo appoynted &amp; proclamed, ſhal haue auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie in the ſheryffes name to make repleuis and delyueraunce of ſuch diſtreſſes, in ſuch maner &amp; fourme, as the ſheryffe, may or ought to do, vpon paine that euery Sheriffe, for euery moneth that he ſhal lacke ſuch deputie, or deputies, ſhall forfayte for euerye ſuche offence fyue poundes, the one halfe of whyoh forfaitures ſhalbe to the kyng &amp; Quenes highnes, her heires and ſucceſſours, the other halfe to him that wil ſue for the ſame by byll, playnt, information, or action of debt, in any the kyng and quenes courtes of record, in which noo eſſoygne protection, nor wager of lawe ſhalbe admytted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An acte appoynting in order to iuſtices of peace touching the baylemente of pryſoners.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .xiii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, in the .iii. yeare of the reigne of the noble prince, king Henrye the ſeuenth, it was among other thinges ordeined &amp; enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that no priſoner arreſted for felony, ſhould be letten to bayle or mainpryſe, by anye one Iuſtice of peace, but by the hole Iuſtices, or at leaſt by two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereof one to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quorum Since the makyng of which eſtatute, one Iuſtice of peace in the name of him ſelf and one other of the Iuſtices hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pagnyon not makyng the ſayd Iuſtice partie nor priuye vnto the ceaſe wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the priſoner ſhould be bayled, hath often tymes by ſiniſter labor and meanes, ſet at large the greateſt, and notableſt offenders, ſuch as be not repliniſable by the lawes of thys realme, &amp; yet the rather to hyde theyr affections in that behalfe haue ſygnyfyed the cauſe of theyr apprehenſion to be put onely for ſuſpition of felony, whereby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25750:30"/>ſayd offendours hath eſcaped vnponiſhed, and do dayly, to the high dyſpleſure of almighty God, the great peryl of the kyng and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes true ſubiectes, and encoragement of al theues and euylldoers. For reformation wherof, be it ordeined and enacted by the kynge and Quenes maieſties, the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, &amp; by aucthoritie of the ſame that from, and after the fyrſt day of Apryll next cominyng no Iuſtice or Iuſtices of peace, ſhall let to baile or mainepryce anye ſuch perſon or perſones, which for any offence or offences, by them or any of them committed be declared not to be repleuiſed or bailed or be forbidden to be repleued, or bailed, by the eſtatute of Weſtmin, prymer, made in the parliamente holden in the thirde yeare of the reygne of kyng Edward the fyrſt. And furthermore, that anye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſones arreſted for manſlaughter or felony, or ſupection of manſlaughter or felony, being bayleable by the lawe, ſhall not after the ſayd fyrſt day of Apryll, be lette to bayle or maynepryſe, by anye Iuſtices of peace, if it be not in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Seſſions, except it be bi two Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices of peace at the leaſt, wherof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> &amp; the ſame iuſtices to be preſent together, at the tyme of the ſayd bailmente or mainpriſe, which bailement or mainpryſe they ſhal certifye in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, ſubſcrybed, or ſygned with their owne handes, at the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall gaole deliuery, to be holden within the countie, wher the ſaid perſon or perſon ſhalbe arreſted or ſuſpected. And that the ſayd Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, or one of them beyng of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> when anye ſuch priſoner is brought before them, for any manſlaughter or felonye, before auye baylement or maynepryce, ſhall take the examination of the ſaid pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoner, and information of them that brynges him, of the facte, &amp; cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces thereof, &amp; the ſame or aſmuch therof, as ſhalbe materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to proue the felony, ſhall put in wrytinges before they make the ſame bailement, which ſaid examination together, with the ſayde baylement, the ſayd Iuſtices ſhall certify at the next generall goale delyuery to be holden within the limites of theyr commiſſyon, and that euery Coroner, vpon any inquiſition before him founde, where by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons ſhalbe indicte for murther, or man ſlaughter or as acceſſary or acceſſaryes to the ſame, before the murder or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter committed, ſhal put in writing the effect of the euydence geuen to the Iurye before him, being materiall, and aſwell the ſayd Iuſtices, as the ſayd Coroner, ſhall haue aucthoritie by thys acte to bind al ſuch by recogniſaunce, or obligation, as do declare any thing material, to proue the ſaid murdre or manſlaughter, offences, or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies, or to be acceſſary, or acceſſaries to the ſame, as is afore ſaid to appeare at the next general gaole deliuery, to be bolden within the Countie, citie, or towne corporat, wher the triall therof ſhalbe, then and there to geue euidence againſt the partie ſo indicted at the time
<pb facs="tcp:25750:30"/>of his triall and ſhall certifie aſwell the ſame euidence, as ſuche bonde and bondes in writing, as he ſhall take together with the inquiſition orindictment before him taken and founde, at, or before the time of his ſayd tryall therof, to be had or made, and lykewyſe, the ſayde Iuſtices ſhall certifye all and euery ſuche bonde, taken before them, in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as before is ſayd of baylementes and examination. And in caſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Iuſtice of peace, or <hi>Quorum,</hi> or Coroner ſhall after the ſayde fyrſt day of apryll, offende in any thinge contrary to the true intente, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this preſent acte: That then the Iuſtices of gaole delyuerye of the Shire, citie, to wue, or place, where ſuch offence ſhall happen to be committed, vpon due profe therof, by examination before them ſhal for euery ſuch offence, ſet ſuch fyne on euery of the ſame Iuſtices of peace and Coroner, as the ſame Iuſtices of gaole deliuery ſhall thinke mete, and ſhall eſtrete the ſame as other fynes and amerciamentes aſſeſſed before Iuſtices of gaole deliuery ought to be.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, that Iuſtices of peace, and Coroners within the citie of London and the countie of Middelſex, and in other cities, boroughes, and tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes corporat within this realme and Wales, ſhall within their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iuriſdictions, haue auctorytie to let to bayle, fellons and priſoners in ſuch maner and fourme, as they haue bene heretofore accuſtomed, this act or any thinge therein conteyned, to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding. And alſo ſhall take examinations and bondes, as is aforeſayde, vpon euery baylement by them or any of them to be made, and ſhal cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifie euery ſuch baylementes, bondes, and examinations, by them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, taken or made at the next gaole deliuery to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſhyre, citie, borough, or towne, where theyr ſeueral iuriſdictions extendeth, vpon like payne and forfeyture, as is before limitted in this preſent acte.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by the auctorytye aforeſaid, that no writers of <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> or <hi>Certiorary,</hi> ſhalbe hereafter graunted to remoue anye pryſoner out of any gaole, or to remoue anye recogniſaunce, except the ſame writtes be ſigned with the proper handes of the chiefe Iuſtyce, or in his abſence, one of the Iuſtices of the courte, oute of whiche the ſame writtes ſhal be awarded, or made, vppon payne that he that wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any ſuche writtes, not beyng ſigned as is aforeſayde, to forfayte to our ſayde ſoueraygne lorde the kynge and the queene, for euerye ſuche writte and writtes fiue poundes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An act for the makyuge of ruſſell ſattens, ſattens reuerſes. and fuſtian of Naples in Norwiche.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .xiiii. Chapter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:31"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here of late yeres paſſed ruſſelles, called ruſſels ſattens and ſattens reuerſes, haue bene practiſed to be made beyonde the ſeas of the wolles bredde in the countye of Norfolke, and by reaſon thereof ſo greate quantytie of the ſayde ruſſelles ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, haue bene brought into this Realme, ſolde and worne as well in euery parte of thys Realme, as in the partes beyond the ſeas, that ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the myſteries of worſtedes makynge and weauynge, whereby marchauntes and inhabitauntes of the Citie of Norwiche, haue here tofore bene well maynteyned and relieued, is nowe at this preſent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt wholy decayed and broughte out of eſtimation, and verye lyttle worne, either within this realme, or in any other forreyne realmes, to the great hynderaunce, and decaye of the ſayde citye, and Citezens of the ſame Citie. For remedy whereof Thomas Marſham, Maiour of the citie of Norwiche Iohn Corbet Eſquier, Auſten Stewarde, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Leche, Robert Rugge, Iohn Ball, and Alexander Mather, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen of the ſayde citie, Thomas Whale, Thomas Pecke, Raphe Marſham, Robert Henry, Iohn Sutton, Rycharde Tomſon, Cyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zins and marchauntes of the ſayde Citie, at theyr greate coaſtes and charges, as well in bringynge of certayn ſtrangers from the partes be yonde the ſeas into the ſayd cytye, as alſo in makinge of Lombes, and all other proniſion for the ſame, and alſo haue called vnto them eyghte perſons of the mooſte diſcrete and worthy men of the miſterye of Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtede weuinge, within the ſayd citie, that is to ſaye, Iohn Cooke, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Lyn. Iohn Croſſe, Simon Petit, Iohn Marſhall, Roger Lecke Edmunde Barker, and Edmunde Selers, beynge the number of .xxi. perſons, which haue not onely made Ruſſels Sattens, and Sattens Reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples within the ſaide citie of Norwiche of Norfolke wolles, but alſo haue learned and taught other citizens and inhabitauntes of the ſaid citie to make the ſame, in ſuche good and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect maner, that muche better Ruſſels Sattens, Sattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, and ſuche lyke, and for eaſyer pryces, be now at thys preſent wrought and made within the ſayd citie, then heretofore hath bene, or nowe be made in anye of the partyes beyonde the ſeas, whereby the ſaid citie and inhabitauntes therof maye and be in lyke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to be relieued and bronghte to the olde eſtate, to the greate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of the commodytyes of thys realme, and enrichynge the ſame, yf ſome good and polytyke lawes and ordynaunces were made for the good continuaunce of the true makynge of the ſayde Ruſſeles Sattens, Sattens Reuerces, and Fuſtyan of Naples, and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof be it enacted by the aſſent of the kynge and queenes hyghnes the Lordes ſpyrytuall and temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parlyament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie
<pb facs="tcp:25750:31"/>of the ſame, that the ſaide ruſſels ſattens, and ſattens reuerſes, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Naples hereafter to be made only within the ſayd citie, maye from henceforth beare the name, and be called by the name of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſattens, and Norwiche fuſtians, and that the maior and the afore mentioned citezens of the ſame citie, which before this tyme hath ben at the coſtes and charges of the bringing of the ſayde ſtraungers into the ſame citie, for the making of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and fuſtians of Naples, and ſuche the afore mentioned eyght per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that they haue called vnto them ſhalbe a felowſhyp of them ſelfes and ſhall yerely the thyrd daye of Februarye chooſe of theyr felowes, foure wardens within the guilde hall of the ſayde citie, or anye other common and conuenient place in the ſame Cytie, and the ſame war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſo beynge chooſen, ſhall ſtande and be wardens of the ſame fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp during one whole yeare, next enſuing the ſaid election &amp; that the ſame wardeynes after the ſayd election ſhall come before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior of the ſayd citie for the tyme being, yerely the mondaye nexte after the ſayde thirde daye of Februarye, and before the ſayde maior ſhalbe ſworne diligentlye to viewe ſearche, and ſee al the ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, then made or that ſhalbe made within the ſayd citie, durynge the ſayde yeare. And ſuche of the ſayde ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, as ſhal apeare and be demed by them to be lawfully truely and workmanly wrought ſhall ſeale with a ſeale of leade, bearyng the armes of the cytie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche, wherby it may be knowen to the marchaunt or buyer of them that the ſame be allowed and truely made.</p>
            <p>And that alſo it maye be enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that the ſayd wardens and felowſhippe ſhalbe a bodye corporate, and to be named and be enabled by this acte to ſue, and be ſued and to geue, and to take by the name of wardeynes and felowſhyppe of the myſterye of ruſſel ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche makynge within the ſaid cytye of Norwiche. And yf any defaulte at anye tyme ſhalbe founde in any of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Norwiche, or in any of them by the ſayde wardeynes, that the ſame default ſhalbe reformed and the offendour or offendoures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be puniſhed accordinge to ſuch rules and ordinaunces, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from time to time ſhalbe made within the ſaid citie by the maior of the ſayd city for the tyme beynge, and by the ſayde foure wardeynes, and the felowſhyppe of the ſayde occupation or miſterye, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of the ſayde felowſhyppe for, and concernynge the ſame, and that the ſame defaultes from time to tyme, as occaſyon ſhall ſerue ſhalbe enquyred of, and tried before the maior of the ſaid cytye of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche for the tyme beynge, by the othes of twelue honeſte menne of the foreſayde felowſhyppe. And that the ſayde foure wardeynes ſo choſen and ſworne, ſhall haue full power &amp; auctoritye, to doo execute,
<pb facs="tcp:25750:32"/>preſente, and reforme all and ſinguler thynge and thinges, of, for, and concernynge the ſayd myſterie, makyng workyng and occupiynge of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes and fuſtian of Norwich with in the ſayde citie in ſuch maner and fourme as in or by the ſayde ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhalbe expreſſed and declared, and that at all tymes hereafter and from tyme to time it ſhalbe lawful to the Maior of the ſayde cytie for the tyme being, and to the before named felowſhyp and wardeyns of the ſame myſterie, and the more parte of theim, &amp; to theyr ſucceſſors, to make and ordeyne from time to time rules, lawes and ordinances mete and neceſſary for the good order and gouernaunce of the ſayde myſtery, and for the true and wel makyng of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche, and the ſame ordinaunces ſo made to be at all times obeied by al thinhabitaunce of the ſaid citie, or ſuburbes of the ſame, &amp; to be put in due execution by the ſaide maior and wardens, and their ſucceſſors for the time being, in ſuch manner &amp; forme as by the ſayd ordinaunce ſhall be ordeyned and declared. And that ſuch as now be and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hereafter ſhalbe makers of the ſaide ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwich, &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd citie ſhall not from henceforth occupy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid myſtery &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, nor anye of them within the ſayd citie by them ſelues, or by anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before he or they ſo occupiyng the ſayde miſtery within the ſayde citie be made free of the ſaid citie, and admitted to be of the ſayd felow ſhip by the maior of the ſayde citie, &amp; wardeyns and felowſhyppe of the ſayd miſtery for the time beyng. And that no perſon do occupy by him ſelfe or anye other for him out of the ſayd citie, the ſaide miſterye of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtians of Naples, or of any of them, before he or they ſo occupiyng the ſame, haue ben prentice to the ſaide miſterye by the terme of ſeuen yeares, or elles admitted by the ſayde maior and felowſhyp or the more part of them, vpon paine of forfeyture of the ſame ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wich by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any of them to be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the forme of this act.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes &amp; be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that the ſayd maior and wardens for the tyme beynge, ſhall not take anye ſumme of money, or reward to theyr owne proper vſes, for the admyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of any perſon or perſons, to occupy the ſaid myſterye vpon paine of forfeyture of treble the value of the reward or ſumme of moneye ſo by them or anye of them to be taken.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that it ſhalbe lawfull to the ſayde wardenes, and to euery of them for the time being, by alwayes and meanes &amp; at al law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full times, dinge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly from time to time, to make ſearche by dewe &amp; ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary waies, for al maner of the ſaide ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche, that ſhal happen to be founde by them defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, for lacke of good and true workmanſhyp. And that it ſhalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:25750:32"/>to the ſayd wardeynes and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the time beinge, by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this acte, to ſeaſe and take the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and fuſtian, &amp; bringe and preſent the ſame clothes ſo ſeaſed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to the Maior of the ſaid citie for the time being, &amp; vnto his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, to thintent that twelue honeſt, lawful, and expert men of the ſaid myſterie, and felowſhip being ſworne before the ſayde Maior, maye by vertue of their othes, make inquirie, and preſent the maner of the ſayde defaultes before the ſaid Maior, for the tyme beyng accordyng to ſuch good and holſom or dinances and rules, as ſhalbe ordeyned and made for the conſeruation and good continuance of the ſayd occupation and miſterie, and the true makyng and working of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtians of Norwich. And that al &amp; euery perſon and perſons, that ſhall occupy, vſe, and exerciſe the ſaid miſterye, or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtians of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiche, or any of them, contrary to the forme, tenour playne meanyng, and intent of this act, and of the rules &amp; ordiaunces, that at any time hereafter by aucthoritie of this acte ſhalbe ordeyned and made for the continuaunce of the true and perfect making of the ſayd ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwich, ſhall forfeyt and loſe for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tyme ſo offending, or making any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche, contrary to the meaning, tenour and effecte of the ſaid acte, rules, and ordinaunces, concerning the ſame, ſuche fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, emerciamentes, and paines as ſhalbe adiudged, aſſeſſed, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by twelue experte men of the ſayd felowſhip vpon theyr othes, the ſame twelue perſons to beſworne before the ſaid Maior and wardens to enquire and make true verdict, and preſentment of ſuch defaultes, the one half of al which forfeyture to be to the Maior of the ſaide citye for the time being, &amp; his ſucceſſors, and thother moitie to the ſaid war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens for the time being, and their ſucceſſors, bi action of det, vil, plaint or information, in any court of record, in which action, vil, plaint or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation no wager of law protection, inuention, or forren Ple, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be allowed. And in caſe it ſhall fortune hereafter, that any of the ſayde ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwich ſhal lack of ſuch lengthes &amp; bredes, or of the true and enſuing making or ſorting of the yarne as ſhalbe appoynted, and ſet forth by the ſayd rules and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and the ſame ſo to be found defectiue by verdicte of twelue men of the ſaid felowſhip before the ſayd Maior and wardeins, and theyr ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſors: That then the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Naples, and euery of them ſo found defectiue, to be cut in two pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to paye ſuch fine or fines as ſhalbe offered &amp; affered by the ſaid twelue expert men by vertue of theyr othes, the one moytye of whiche fyne or fines to be to the Maior of the ſayd citie for the tyme being, and to his ſucceſſors and thother moytie to the wardeynes of the ſayde fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp for the tyme beyng, and to theyr ſucceſſours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25750:33"/>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, that if any wardeyne or wardeines for the time beyng of the ſaid miſterie or occupation of makinge ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, ſhal at any tyme hereafter ſeale, or cauſe to be ſealed any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, or fuſtians of Naples, that ſhal not be wel ſufficient and truely wrought, and made accordyng to the true entent and meanyng of thys preſent act, ſhal forfeyt &amp; looſe for euery pece ſo ſealed, beyng not well ſufficient and trulye wrought and made, the whole value of euery ſuche pece ſo ſealed, thone halfe of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che forfeytures to be to the kynge and Queenes maieſties, her heyres and ſucceſſors, and thother moytye therof to be to ſuch perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons as ſhall ſue for the ſame by byll, action, or information, in anye of the kynges courtes of record, in whiche byll, action, or information no eſſoygne protection, or wager of lawe ſhalbe allowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An act to confyrme the liberties of the lorde Marchers in Wales.</head>
            <head type="sub">The .xv. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vmbly beſechen your excellente maieſties, youre true and faythfull Subiectes, the lorde Marchers bothe ſpyrytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall, within your hyghnes dominion of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that where as in the parliament holden at Weſtm. the xxvii. yeare of the raygne of kynge Henry theyght, father vnto you oure naturall Soueraygne ladye, amongeſt other thinges one acte was made and eſtabliſhed for lawes and inſtice to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the ſayde dominion of Wales, inlyke fourme as it is in thys realme of England, in the whiche acte one article is, that for that the lordes Marchers before the parliament had vſed to put theyr tenaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes within the lordſhips Marchers, vnder common maynpryce and ſuerty of apparaunce, and haue had the forfeytures thereof, which for euer from and after the feaſt of al ſainctes then next enſuyng the ſayde parliament ſhoulde vtterlye ſeaſe, and be determyned. It was enacted that after the ſayd feaſt of all ſaynctes, euery lay and temporall perſon then beyng a lorde Marcher, ſhoulde haue the moitye or halfe of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forfeyture of all and euery common mainpryce, recogniſance for the peace or apparaunce, forfeyted by anye of their tenauntes inhabitinge within any of theyr lordſhips marchers, and they to be payed the ſame moytie or halfe by the handes of the ſhyriffe of euerye of the countyes where ſuch forfeyture ſhalbe, yf the ſhyryff can leuye the ſame, and the ſame ſhyriffe to accompte to our ſayde late ſoueraygne lorde the kynge for the other half or moytie, in ſuche excheker as they can be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tant. And further it was enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that all and euery lay, and temporall perſon or perſons, then beyng lords marchers and hauyng any lordſhyps marchers, or lordſhips royall ſhoulde from and after the ſayd feaſt of al ſayuctes, haue all ſuch myſes and profytes
<pb facs="tcp:25750:33"/>of their tenantes, as they haue had or vſed to haue at the fyrſte entrye into theyr landes in times paſt. And alſo ſhould haue hold &amp; kepe, with in the precinct of theyr lordeſhippes, courtes Baron, courtes lete, and lawdayes, and all and euery thing to the ſayd courtes belonging, and alſo ſhuld haue within the precinct of their ſaid lordſhips, or lawdaye wayf, ſtrayf, infangthefe, outfangthefe, treaſure trouie, deodandes, goodes and cattels of fellons, and of perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned or outlawed of fellony or murther, put in exigente for fellonye or murther, and alſo wrecke de mer, wharfage, and cuſtomes of ſtraungers, as they haue had in time paſte, as thoughe ſuch priuileges graunted vnto them by poynt of charter, any thing in that acte to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as in the ſaid act of parliament more at large it may appeare.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as biſhops, and other eccleſiaſtical perſons beynge lordes marchers, hauing the like liberties, caſualties, profittes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, within their iordſhyps marchers, and lordſhips royal, with in the ſayd dominion, or principalitie of Wales, were not prouided for by the expreſſe letter of the ſayde ſtatute, in like ſorte as the laye and temporall lordes marchers were, but rather of purpoſe as it ſhoulde ſeme forgotten and lefte out of the ſayde acte, agaynſte all reaſon and good equitie: And foraſmuch alſo, as the heyres and ſucceſſoures of the lay and temporal lordes marchers, then beinge were not prouided for, by the limitation and expreſſe wordes of the ſayd acte, as well as their aunceſters &amp; predeceſſors were, as reaſon wold thei ſhulde haue bene.</p>
            <p>It may pleaſe your maieſties of your mooſt gratious fauoure and benignitie at the humble ſuit and ſupplication of youre ſayde faythfull ſubiectes the lordes marchers that nowe are, in the ſayd dominion of Wales, both ſpiritual and temporal, to graunt that it maye by thaſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, be ordeined, eſtabliſhed, and enacted, by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of this preſent parliament, that aſwel your ſaid ſpiritual and ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſubiectes, lordes marchers, now hauinge lordſhippes mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or lordſhips royal in Wales aforeſayde, and their ſucceſſors, and the ſucceſſoures of euerye of them, as alſo the heyres and ſucceſſoures of the lordes temporall marchers, that then were or nowe be, and the heyres or ſucceſſours of euery of them beyng, or whiche hereafter ſhall belordes marchers within their lordſhips marchers, and lorſhyppes royal in the dominion or principalitie of Wales, ſhall haue and enioye to them and to their heires &amp; ſucceſſors, reſpectiuely and ſeuerallye for euer the moytie &amp; half of euery forfeyture, of al &amp; euery common main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price recogniſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the peace or apparaunce forfeyted by anye theyr tenantes inhabiting w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in any of their lordſhips marchers, or lordſhips royal, &amp; they to be payde the ſame moytie or halfe by the handes of the ſhyriffe of the countie, for the time beyng, after ſuche forme and ſort as the ſayd lay or temporal lordes marchers haue bene or oughte to haue
<pb facs="tcp:25750:34"/>bene payed the ſame, by force of the ſayde Statute.</p>
            <p>And further, ſhall haue all ſuch miſes, &amp; profites of their tenauntes, as the lordes marchers, ſpirituall or temporall, reſpectiuely, or ſeuerallye had or vſed to haue at theyr fyrſt entry into their landes in times paſt before the makyng of the ſayd act or ſtatute. And alſo ſhall haue, hold and kepe within the precinct of their ſayd lordſhips, al ſuch courtes ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ron courtes lete, and lawdayes, and al and euery thing and thinges, to the ſame courtes belonging, and alſo ſhal haue within the precincte of theyr ſayd ſeuerall lordſhippes, or lawdayes, all ſuche waif, ſtraif, in fang thefe, outfang thefe, treaſure trouis, deodamdes, goodes, and cat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tels of fellons, and of perſons condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned or outlawed of fellonye or murther, put in exigent for fellony or murther, and alſo al ſuch wreck demer, wharfage, &amp; cuſtomes of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, as the lordes Marchers, ſpyrytuall and temporall, reſpectiuely, and ſeuerallye had and vſed in tymes paſt, before the makyng of the ſayd ſtatute.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>☞ An act for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap .xvi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Her in the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t begon &amp; holden at London the, iii. daye of Nouember. in the .xxi. yeare of the raigne of our moſt dread ſouerain lord of moſt famous memory, king Henry theight, &amp; from thence adiourned to Weſtm. and there holden &amp; continued by diuers prorogations, vnto the diſſolution therof, one act was made and eſtabliſhed for the reſtraint of cariage, &amp; conueying of horſes, &amp; mares out of this realme, &amp; alſo one other act was there made for the true windinge of wolles, and one other act was there made, to reſtrain killing of wain linges, bullocks, ſtieres, &amp; heifers, being vnder thage of .ii. yeres which ſayd ſeueral actes were then made to endure &amp; continue to the nexte parliament, as by the ſaid ſeuerall actes more playnly appeareth. And wher alſo in the ſaid parliament, one other act was made &amp; eſtabliſhed for attaintes to be ſued for the puniſhment of periury, vpon vntrue ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dites, which actes laſt before reherſed, were then made and ordeined, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; endure to the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as by the ſame act more playnely at large is ſhewed &amp; may apeare. And wher alſo in the parliament begon and holden at Weſt. theyght day of Iune, in the xxviii. yere of the raygne of our ſayd moſt drad ſoueraigue lord kynge Henry the .viii. and ther continued &amp; kept vnto the diſſolution thereof it was ordeined and enacted, that al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred, &amp; euery of them, ſhould continue &amp; endure in their force and ſtrength, &amp; alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntyl the laſt day of the nexte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by the ſame act amonges other thinges therein conteyned more plainly appeareth. And where alſo in the parliament begon and holden at Weſt. the .xxviii. day of aprill in the .xxxi. yeare of the raigne of our ſayd late moſt dread ſoueraigne lord king Henry the eyght, and
<pb facs="tcp:25750:34"/>there continued vntill the .xxviii. day of Iune then next folowing it was ordeined and enacted by thaucthoritie of the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid ſeueral actes aboue remembred &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; al clauſes, articles, &amp; prouiſions in them, &amp; euery of them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned, ſhould coutinue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntil the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as by the ſame acte a mongs other thinges therein contained, more playnly appeareth. And wher in the parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtm. in the xxxv. yeare of the raigne of our ſaid late ſoueraigue lord king Henry theight, on act was made for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of woods, to endure for vil. yeares then next folowyng, &amp; from thence to thend of the next parliamet, as by the ſame act more playnly doth &amp; may appeare. And wher alſo at the parliament holden at Weſt. in the .xxxvii. yere of the raigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd king Henry theight, &amp; ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued and kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof it was ordeined &amp; enacted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes abou mentioned &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepte the ſaid act made for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of wodes, as is aforſaid, ſhuld continue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtrenght, &amp; alſo to be obſerued &amp; kept, vntil the laſt day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then folowing, as by the ſame act amongs other things ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in conteined more playnly appeareth. And wher alſo at the ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ended at Weſtm. in the xiiii. day of March, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third yere of the reigne of our ſoueraigne Lord kyng Edward the ſyxte, one acte was made for the true curriyng of leather, which acte was made to endure to thend of the next parliament, as by the ſame acte more playnly appeareth. And wher alſo at the ſeſſyon of a Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ended at Weſt. the firſt day of February, in the fourthe yeare of the reigne of our ſaid late ſoueraigne Lord kind Edward the .vi. one acte was then &amp; ther made, concerning the buying of rother bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes. And alſo one other act was then &amp; ther made touching the dui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſelling of butter &amp; cheſe, which ſayd ſeueral actes, were then &amp; there made, to endure &amp; continue, to the ende of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as by the ſame ſeuerall actes more at large it doth and may appere. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by prorogation holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. the xxiii. day of Ianuary in the v. yeare of the reign of our ſaid ſoneraygne lord, one other act was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ther made, agaynſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratours and forſtallers to endure to thend of the next parliament which al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue mentioned together, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid act concerning theyreſeruation of wodes, at a parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtm. the fyrſt day of March, in the vii. yeare of the raygne of our ſaid ſoueraigne Lord King Edwarde the .vi. &amp; there contynued and dyſſolued the laſt day of the ſame moneth of March, &amp; al clauſes articles &amp; prouiſions in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; euery of them conteined were there re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiued &amp; continued, to ſtand in their force &amp; ſtrength, vntil the laſt dai of the next parliament. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliament holden by prorogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxiiii. day of October, in the .i. yeare
<pb facs="tcp:25750:35"/>of the raygne of our moſt gratious ſoueraygne lady y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene, &amp; there contynued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution therof, one act was ther made &amp; eſtabliſhed againſt vnlawful &amp; revellyous aſſembles, to endure to thend of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parliament as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act mor plainli doth &amp; maye appeare. And wher alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, laſt before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oned, al &amp; ſinguler y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acts aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned &amp; before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued at at ſundri parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as is aforeſiad, &amp; clauſes, articles, &amp; prouiſions in them and euery of them conteyned, wer their reuiued, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to ſtand in their force and ſtrength, vnto the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Foraſmuche as al &amp; ſynguler the ſayd ſeueral actes aboue mentioned be good &amp; beneficial for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common wealth of this realme Be it therfore enacted ordeined &amp; eſtabliſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king &amp; quene our ſoueraigne lord &amp; lady with thaſſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual &amp; temporal &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parliament aſſembled &amp; by thaucthoritie of the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al and ſinguler the ſeueral acts &amp; eſtatutes aboue menti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oned &amp; rehearſed, &amp; euery of them and al clauſes articles, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; euerye of them conteyned, ſhalbe reuiued, continued, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; endure in theyr force &amp; ſtrength, to al intentes, conſtrutcions, &amp; purpoſes &amp; ſhall be obſerued and kepte in al thynges, vntil the laſt day of the next parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>An acte touchyng leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpiritual perſones. Cap .xvii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begon &amp; holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. the eight day of Iune, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxviii. year of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> raigne of our lat king of famous memory He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry theight, &amp; ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution of the ſame parliament, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xviii. dai of Iune next folowing, one act intituled, an act for reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt fruytes in the tyme of vacatyon, to the nexte incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bente, was had &amp; made wherin are certeine clauſes for leaſes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, &amp; to be made biſpiritual &amp; eccleſiaſtical perſons, to endure, &amp; be in force for terme of, vi. yeares if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incumbentes did reſigne ther ſaid ſpiritual promoti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhuld otherwiſe becom void bi thonli act of the ſame thincumbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, is bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act mor at large may appeare. To thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons &amp; vicares &amp; others hauing cure of ſoules may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, and be the more vigylaunt in thir miſterye and function.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by the king our ſoueraigne lord, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene our ſoue raigne lady with thaſſentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual &amp; temporal &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled &amp; by aucthoritie of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſmuch of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame acte, as doth conſerne the making good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ieaſesne any clauſe, ſentence, prouiſion, or article therein conteyned ſhal extend, or be conſtrued, or adiudged to extend to any leaſe, that ſhalbe made by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vicar or any other haing any ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motion, after the feaſt of the purificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lady next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Excuſum Londini in aedibus Iohannis Cavvodi, Tipographi Regiae Maiestatis. Anno M.D.L.V</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
